Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: rise for the arrival of the Senate president, the presiding officer, and several judges of the impeachment court.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: The
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: sergeant at arms is directed to make a proclamation.
Alfredo Sotto Corpuz: All persons are commanded to keep silent under pain of penalty while the impeachment court is in session for the trial of Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: The impeachment trial of Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte is hereby called to order. We shall be led in prayer by Senator-Judge Vicente C. Sotto III.
Sen. Vicente C. Sotto III: Almighty and merciful God, we come before you with humility as our nation enters a solemn and consequential moment in the impeachment proceedings.
Sen. Vicente C. Sotto III: We pray that you guide every person entrusted with this constitutional process, especially each senator who will sit as a judge. Grant us who are gathered in this august chamber integrity, good faith, courage, and sound judgment. Keep our hearts free from political pressure, personal interests, prejudice, anger, and fear. May we seek not what is convenient or popular, but what is right. Just and faithful to the truth. Dear Lord Father God, remind each of us that our duty is not to any individual, party, or faction. Our duty is to you, to the Filipino people, and to the Constitution. Give us the wisdom to weigh the evidence carefully, the fairness to listen with an open mind, and the courage to make decisions according to our conscience and the law. May truth prevail over rumor, facts over speculation, and justice over politics. Let every proceeding be conducted with dignity, fairness and respect for the rule of law. Dear Lord, protect our country from division and hatred. Give our people patience, discernment, and faith in the proper institutions of our republic. May your wisdom guide us, may your justice lead us, and may your truth prevail. Amen.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: Amen. The clerk of court will now call the roll.
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: Call call up members. Senator-Judge Aquino, Senator-Judge Cayetano-Allan, Senator-Judge Cayetano-Pia, Senator-Judge De La Rosa, Senator-Judge O'Hercito, Senator-Judge Estrada, senator-judge Goh, senator-judge Ontiveros, senator-judge Lacson, senator-judge Lapid, senator-judge Legarda, senator-judge Marcoleta, senator-judge Marcos, senator-judge Padilla, senator-judge Pangilinan, senator-judge Soto III, senator-judge Tulfo Erwin, senator-judge Tulfo Raffi, senator-judge Villanueva, senator-judge Villar Camilo, senator-judge Villar Marc, senator-judge Zubiri. The presiding officer, Senator-Judge Escudero, Senate President Gachaliet.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: With 18 center judges present, the chair declares the presence of a quorum. In accordance with the rules of procedure in impeachment trials, the chair now recognizes the duly elected presiding officer to preside over the proceedings of the impeachment court.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you, Mr. Senate President. If there are no objections, we shall dispense with the reading of the journal. of the Senate Citizenship and Impeachment Court, dated August 5, 2026, and shall consider the same as approved.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The court will please, the clerk of court will please call the case before the impeachment court.
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: Case number 004, 2026, in the matter of impeachment trial, Vice-President Saira Zimmerman, Duterte.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Appearances of the parties.
Rep. Joel R. Chua: Same appearance for the prosecution, Your Honor. We are ready.
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: Same appearance for the respondent, Your Honor. We're ready.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you and good morning to the counsel for the parties. Yes, Honorable Chua, what is your pleasure?
Rep. Joel R. Chua: Your Honor, I understand that this is a continuation of the examination of the prosecution's witness. May we request that Attorney Kapunan, counsel for the prosecution, be recognized, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, Attorney Kapunan is recognized.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Attorney Lorna and Attorney Cristina, I understand that the parties were not able to meet during the two rainy days.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: I
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: understand that the parties were not able to meet the last two days of last week. perhaps given the inclement weather, but the fact remains is you were not able to meet.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: May I make manifestations, Your Honor?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, Matar Ni Kapunan.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: First of all, Your Honor, we, this honorable court and presiding officer will note that when we broke off last Wednesday, it was very clear that prosecution through this representation made a motion, in fact modified the motion, that we be allowed to present The documents, 4,492 documents before the honorable clerk of court. And for purposes of comparison, Your Honor, and this honorable presiding judge will recall that it did issue a directive to the parties to make themselves available on Thursday and Friday of last week,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: just
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: mutually agreeing on a on common time, Your Honor. Also, the clerk of court was directed to make themselves available either on Tuesday or Friday or both days subject to a time agreed upon by both counsels for the petitioner and the respondent. Ito pong nangyari na indyan po kami. Why do I say that? Wednesday we made a text message and I have the text messages here. When do we meet? Tomorrow or Friday? Wala pong sagot noong Wednesday. On Thursday, we waited the whole day. Kailan tayo magme-meet? Thursday na ngayon. Friday na bukas. Our witness will be on board on Monday. Wala pa rin sagot, Your Honor. The whole day of Thursday. At the end of Thursday, at the end of office hours, Thursday, Your Honor, and we have the evidence here, at 5.38 in the afternoon of Thursday, they texted, counsel for the respondent texted to say, we are available on August 14. This coming Friday, Your Honor, August 14. When napakalinaw naman sa directive ng presiding officer na mag-agree on a date on Thursday or Friday of last week, August 14, what good will that do us? The hearing is today, August 10, and they want us to appear before the Clerk of Court to compare documents on August 14. For what purpose, Your Honor? Now, The text message is even more disturbing because apart from saying sa August 14 na lang, they even disclaimed the fact that this honorable court said Thursday or Friday last week wala naman daw sinabi ang presiding officer except to set a time, date, and time mutually agreed upon by the parties. That is bad faith, Your Honor, because Sinabi ng presiding officer ang specific dates Thursday or Friday last week.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Wala daw sinabi ang presiding officer. And the presiding officer will recall that you left it to the parties, Your Honor, to agree on the time but not on the dates. Now we are told August 14.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: The
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: clerk of court over the weekend also was waiting for notice from both parties. and we got a call from the clerk of court saying walang sinabi sa amin except August 40.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: In a last attempt, Your Honor, in a last attempt for them, for counsels, for the respondent, this morning, as late as this morning, we approached them to say, we have one hour to go, let's start. And they said, again, they refused.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: They refused no need daw kasi pakitahan na lang ng summaries, etc., no need, Your Honor. Let me just say, Your Honor, that this attitude of the respondent is not new. We had the same attitude pre-trial pa lang. Ayaw na mag-stipulate. Why? Because daw,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: hindi
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: faithful reproduction, yung kopya nila tsaka yung kopya namin. Bakit hindi faithful reproduction? Because ang pinag-awayan, Presiding Officer, Your Honors, isa lang ang pinag-awayan, covering page. Covering page ng 4,492 documents na yan. Ang pinag-awayan, covering page. And that's why they did not want to stipulate. So, Your Honors, if I may,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: we will necessarily have to go over, very briefly, This witness briefly glossing over the documents and identifying her summary, her tabulation, pursuant to the presiding officer's suggestion, and we are invoking as well Rule 130, Section 7 and Section 3C on summaries and tabulations. We will do that, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: I have
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: a question, counsel. Before I recognize Attorney Lorna, Attorney Wamil had a table and summary for the ARs for December 21 to 31, 2022, which was turned over to Ms. Aileen, so she can testify on that as well, given that it's official records. My question is, does she have a tabulation and or summary? Because apparently, Atty. Wamil did not. Dahil hindi na roon niya inabutan yon, ayon sa kanya, di ba? May tabulation at summary ba si Ms. Cylene ng first to third quarter of 2023 ng OVP at DepEd Confidential Funds?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yes, Your Honor. Our witness, Ma'am Cylene May Del Campo, does have a similar summary of all. of the acknowledgement receipts, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Again, to clarify, covering the first to the third quarters of 2023 of both DPED and OVP?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yes, Your Honor. For the first quarter of the OVP, the second quarter and the third quarter, Your Honor, that totals 1,823 acknowledgement receipts.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: How many? 1,000?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: For the first quarter of... For the first quarter of February 6, March 29, 2023, covering 519 documents, our witness will pass a tabulation, Your Honor, a summary. For the second quarter, which is the period April 25 to June 30, 2023, covering 530 acknowledgment receipts, Your Honor, our witness also will be presenting a tabulation or a summary. And for the third quarter of the Office of the Vice President, our witness will be presenting a tabulation for the periods July 14, September 30, 2023, covering 774 documents, Your Honor. totaling 1,823. And she will confirm as well the tabulation made for the December 2022, 21 to 31, 22 tabulation of Attorney Wamil consisting of 845 documents. So for the Office of the Vice President, this witness will be presenting and identifying 2668 acknowledgement receipts. Likewise, Your Honor, if I may continue.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel May, for the DepEd.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: For the DepEd, Your Honor, for the first quarter covering the period February 20 to March 30, 2023, are witnessed as a tabulation of 561 acknowledgement receipts. For the second quarter, Covering the period April 25 to June 30, 2023, our witness is the tabulation of 619 acknowledgement receipts. And for the third quarter of the deathbed, covering the period July 14 to September 30, 2023, our witness will be identifying and as well the tabulation. of 644 acknowledgement receipts or for the DepEd a total of 1,824 documents which will bring us to 2,668 for the Office of the Vice President, 1,824 for the DepEd totaling 4,492 documents which counsel for the respondent refused, Your Honor, to stipulate on. We are now therefore constrained to present this witness and the tabulations before this Honorable Court.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: She can testify based on the tabulation that she has, again, in accordance with the ruling of the Chair, citing Rule 130, Section 3C, in relation to... Section 7, which is an exception to the original document rule. Your comment, Attorney Christine, before we proceed? Just
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: one more manifestation, Your Honor. In addition to these tabulations, Your Honor, we will be presenting, but not identifying, we will be presenting folders containing these acknowledgement receipts so that the witness can flip over them, Your Honor. Just flip over them. If counsel will say, we are not given the opportunity first, they've been given the opportunity. They refused. And the reason being, number one,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: they
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: don't have enough lawyers, though. We heard in an interview that they did not have enough lawyers and could not schedule, could not follow the directive of the presiding officer. Fifteen. Fifteen lawyers for the defense, for the respondent. They did not have enough lawyers, nor the time to comply with the directive of this honorable presiding officer. Lastly, Your Honor, in any eventual honor, there is no denial of due process. They will have the opportunity when all of these documents are presented in a formal offer of evidence. That is their time to compare. That is their time to make their comments. That is their time to raise their objections, Your Honor, when it is formally offered in evidence in due course. Thank you, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Chair notes the manifestation of Attorney Lorna and her point with respect to the respondent having the opportunity to comment once formal offer has been made. Is well taken. Attorney Christine, yes, your comment, ma'am? Before we proceed?
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: Yes, Your Honor, please. I would like to thank the good counsel for their willingness to explore or to implement Rule 130, Section 7. At least we have aligned with what we are expected to do before this honorable court. In fact, Your Honor, earlier this morning, I was asked by one of her partners about the comparison, and they actually told her partner, attorney Lazaro. Attorney, we don't even need to compare the exhibits in order to expedite the proceedings because first of all, you know, that's the authenticity of the exhibits is something that the court will have to decide.
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: The court will only decide on that after the prosecution has already submitted their offer of evidence and that will be subject to our comment. And there's no need for us to actually compare the exhibits just so we can arrive at a stipulation that this and that are the same. And also, Your Honor, With regard to the identification of the witness of the exhibits, that goes into the witness' competence. We did not stipulate here in open court that the witness is competent to identify the exhibits, Your Honor. kasi hindi naman namin kilala ho yung taga COA. Pangalawa, we don't know the extent of her examination of the documents. Pangatlo, she just assumed the work of Mr. Wamil. So, mahirap naman po sabihin nun ng kliyente namin, sige, okay na, payag na kami, she can identify the exhibit, she knows all of those, she has examined all of those. Precisely, that's the duty of the counsel to do in open court. Now, there's Rule 130, Section 7, And for those of you who are litigating before the CTA, you already know this rule that a witness can testify based on a summary and that would actually show that he's competent. to testify on the exhibits by reason of the summary that she made. And that would attest that she has examined all of the documents that are contained in the summary. That's why yun po yung sinagest ko sa counsel ng kabila. Sabi ko, we don't even, we will not even object, attorney, as to how many exhibits you will identify or you will have as samples kahit sampu per quarter or kahit 100 or kahit wala. Di ba? If you check Rule 130, Section 7, hindi naman hong ni-record. na isa-isahin ho yun. At hindi ho nire-require, Your Honor, na kailangan ho namin mag-stipulate on the exhibits, on the authenticity, so that they can use Rule 130, Section 7. And if properly done po, Your Honor, I think they can identify or they can finish all one quarter in less than 10 minutes. I'm talking about that, no? I'm talking about that based on experience. So, Your Honor, we don't object to their Implementation of Rule 130, Section 7 as to the manner by how they will do it. We will also not object but subject to cross-examination, Your Honor. Thank you.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The manifestation of attorney Christine is noted. Chair will make a ruling so that we can move on.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: May I just respond to this, Your Honor?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The chair did make an order for the parties to try to meet Friday or Thursday. However, for whatever reason, lack of lawyers or inclement weather, that did not happen. Chair, we'd just like to correct, hindi ka attorney-law na inindyan, baka ginos ka, kasi hindi ka sinagot eh, pero hindi ka inindyan, wala namang pinag-usapan date pa eh.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Inignore.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Ghost na nga eh. Ghost na yung bago ngayon. Ghost na yung bago ngayon. Ghosting. But having said that, the Chair notes, because the Chair also inquired, that given what happened in the pretrial, wherein the copies of the exhibits marked by the respondent, no copies were retained by the court. So the Chair would like to request The counsels for respondent to kindly furnish the court with a copy of the marked pieces of evidence during pretrial because apparently we have pre-marked pieces of evidence from the prosecution but not all the pre-marked pieces of evidence from the respondent. So in lieu of meeting, kindly just submit that, Attorney Christine, so that We can do the comparison ourselves, either as a court or through the individual senator-judges.
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: We will comply, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly do that within the day or at the latest tomorrow, if you have it with you, within the day, if not, at the latest of tomorrow, so that whatever may happen, the court will already have a copy of these pre-marked documents. In relation to Ms. Aileen. As stated by Attorney Christine already, they will not object to the presentation of a table and our summary, citing Rule 130, Section 7, in relation to 3C. Therefore, we may proceed with her and hopefully be able to finish also Ms. Pareja today. Counsel, can you proceed?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, please, can I just make a brief manifestation?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, Attorney Kapunan.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: While really, indeed, Section 7, Rule 130 is applicable.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: May we note that this summary, Your Honor, is being used to establish the rulings, the provision says, when the facts sought to be established is only the general result of the whole. So that summary will just establish the fact that this were the very same documents given by the defense counsel to the COA, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: And that these were the very same documents or ARs used by the COA in coming out with the respective issuances that they did?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yes, Your Honor.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: To include the AOMs, the notices of suspension and the notice of disallowance.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: If we can get that from, because we don't want to be held in ambush with subsequent witnesses who will use some portions of this acknowledgement receipts for subsequent witnesses, Your Honor, who we have subpoenaed for this. For this impeachment proceeding, Your Honor, they might say, and I don't want to speculate or I don't want to, anyway, ghosting Bayon. I don't want... to anticipate the strategy, but we will have subsequent witnesses who will testify to specific acknowledgement receipts, Your Honor. And they might say, you did not identify them, you only identified the summaries. So, Your Honor, if we can get a stipulation now from counsel for the defense that when an acknowledgement receipt is presented through another witness, Your Honor, they will not object because precisely they stipulated that the summary...
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, again, let's abbreviate the proceedings. That's always subject to cross. Subject
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: to cross, Your Honor. If
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: you present a document and their copy says otherwise, then they can confront the witness during cross-examination. That's the difference of that document. But if not, then I guess they will skip crossing the witness on that point. as an implied admission that indeed the document she based it on or the document she testified on is indeed the same copy as what they do. But by that time, counsel, we will have a copy already of both documents and the court can make the appropriate ruling at the appropriate time.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: One last, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, Atty. Kapunan. Atty. Lorna.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: We would have preempted. We would have saved this honorable court considerable time if they just agreed to use their documents. We don't need, even this clerk of court, even the presiding officer, even the honorable judges, don't need to make comparison. We are amenable to use the defense exhibits, Your Honor. May I ask these exhibits, Your
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Honor? Attorney Lorna, the chair considered that too when you made that manifestation. However, as I said, Given the fact that we don't have a copy, I guess you don't have a copy too of their exhibits. So they would have to sift through each and every exhibit marked with their own marking to look for, let's say, a particular name in the AR. So once we get the copy, we will furnish you with a copy. And you can use that copy, if you wish, at the appropriate time as well. So, asking for a copy will solve many issues, Attorney Lorna. Attorney Christine, yes,
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: you want to... Quick reply, Your Honor. Actually, it doesn't matter if they will use our own exhibits, Your Honor. It doesn't even make their witness competent. That is why we are here in open court to establish the competence. So kahit paggamitin namin yung exhibit namin, kung hindi naman yung competent yung witness nyo, to identify those... exhibit. It will still be a waste of time. It will be useless.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you for that, counsel. Let's now move on. Call your witness, Attorney Capunan, Attorney Lorna. Clerk of Court is directed to kindly escort or assist Ms. Cylene May Del Ocampo to the witness stand.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, we'd like to call our witness, Ms. Cylene May L. Del Ocampo.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Ms. Aileen, before you sit down, do you understand that you will be continuing with your testimony before this honorable impeachment court under the same oath that you made and was given when you last appeared on Wednesday?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You may sit down, ma'am.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Thank you.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: And good morning. Attorney Capunan, your witness, you may proceed with your cross. Again, sorry, with one more short reminder. You don't have to flip through the individual ARs anymore. We understand that, Attorney Capunan. We will rely on her table and or summary for the meantime. Unless there is a specific AR that you want her to identify and read for the record, then she may simply look at that particular one. But no need to flip. through the entire 4,492 ARs just to show that she indeed prepared her table and summary based on the ARs. That is deemed understood already by the court. You may proceed, Attorney Laura.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: With the permission of this honorable court, good morning. Good morning to the presiding officer, to the impeachment judges, and good morning, counsel. Good morning. The respondent. Good morning, Madam Witness. Good morning po. Are you comfortable? Would you like to come closer to the mic?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Parang nagkwekentuhan lang tayo. Be comfortable, okay? Now, we will continue with where we broke off at the last hearing when you were here and we had preliminary questions. But I regret that I have to ask you again because just... Earlier, this counsel for the respondent is questioning your competence. Madam Witness, can you remind us again, how long have you been with the COA?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: I have been with COA for the past 11 years. Actually, Magdi, 12 years na po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: As COA.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And what was your educational background, Madam Witness? Saan ka nag-aral?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: I earned po my bachelor degree in Bachelor of Science in Accountancy from St. Louis University po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At pagkatapos mo nag-graduate sa St. Louis University, saan ka nagtrabaho?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ang una ko pong naging trabaho is as junior auditor sa isang private firm po sa Baguio City.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And after that?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: After two years po, nag-apply na po ako sa COA at doon na po ako nag-start noong August 26, 2014.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: August 26?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: 2014 po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. And earlier you said that you were in COA ICFAW, correct? Yes po. And what particular activity or duties did you have with this office?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ang mga naging duties ko po sa Kuwaikfaw is first to conduct post-audit of the liquidation documents of various government agencies sa liquidation po niya la sa Intelligence and Confidential Fund and draft po an audit observation memorandum, notice of suspension or notice of disallowance po as may be warranted under rules and regulations on settlement of accounts. And after pong mag-respond noong agency, ako rin po ang nag-evaluate ng mga responses po. sa mga AOM
Cylene May L. Del Campo: at notice of suspension.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So based on your narration, 11 years muna ginagawa to, nag-i-issue ng audit, observation, memorandum, notice of suspension, notice of disallowance, at pinag-aaralan rin ang mga response ng mga national agencies na covered ng Confidential and Intelligence Fund.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po, tama po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Tell us, Madam Witness, how many of these national agencies, local government units, public officials, have you conducted a post-audit?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yung sa national government agencies po, more than 20 na. Sa local po, madami-dami na rin po, mga more than 50. Sa GOCCs naman po, mga less than 10, mga 5 to 10 po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So more than
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: 20 national agencies, tama? More than 30, 50 local government units?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Mga GOCCs po, mga less than 10.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. So when you took over, nung ikawan ng takeover, kay Atty. Wamil, noong February, when he retired or was transferred to another COA office in February 2024, you were then, at that time, also in COA Iqbal.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po, tama po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And ano naman ang participation mo, if any, dito sa pag-post-audit ng confidential funds ng Office of the Vice President at ng DepEd Secretary?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Sa Office of the Vice President po, ang naging participation ko po is dun sa for the period December 21 to 31, 2022, ako po ang nag-evaluate ng response nila sa notice of suspension. Dun naman po sa first to third quarters ng 2023, ako po ang nag-evaluate sa response nila sa mga audit observation memorandum. Sa DepEd naman po, ako po ang nag-evaluate ng responses nila. para dun sa dalawang AOM for the first to third quarters of 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay, Madam Witness,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: you took over the functions or you took over yung mga inaudit ni Atty. Wamil. Are you aware na gumawa siya ng isang tabulation tungkol sa acknowledgement receipts for the last quarter of the Office of the Vice President, December 21 to 30? Are you aware na merong ginawang tabulation si Atty. Wamil?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, po. Aware po ako sa tabulation ni Mr. Wamil.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: If this tabulation is shown to you and for purposes of identification, Your Honor, this has been previously marked in evidence as P-1. dash 29 for the prosecution. Showing to you, Madam Witness, please go over this tabulation prepared, and may we ask permission for attorney, our associate, Attorney J. de la Cruz, to be allowed to present this to the witness.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Assistant counsel of the parties may approach.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Forthe record, Your Honor, the witness is going over the tabulation submitted and marked. by Attorney Wamil and it is Exhibit P
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: -1-29.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted and made part of the records.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Do you confirm, Madam Witness, that ito ang tabulation na sinubmit ni Atty. Wamil sa COA ICFAW Office na minana mo sa kanya?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, po. Ito po yung tabulation na kasama po dun sa mga documents na na-forward sa akin.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: After you received these documents from Attorney Wamil through the office of the COVA-ICFA, what happened next?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: After po ma-issue yung notice of suspension sa OOBP, nag-submit po sila ng response noong March 13, 2024 po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Itong response na
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: sinasabi mo, meron ka bang kopya and if shown to you? If yon to you, itong response ng Office of the Vice President, will you be able to identify the same?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, for easy reference of the presiding officer and this impeachment court, may we ask permission to flash it in the screen, Your Honor?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel may do so.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You're referring to Exhibit P-1-13-B?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yes, Your Honor.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: and respondents 1-120 OBP. This
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: is stipulated document, Your Honor. May
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: I
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: proceed, counsel?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sothe counsel for the defense is now looking at it.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Madam Witness, having gone over this document, Madam Witness, ito ba yung sinasabi mong letter response ng Office of the Vice President?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, po. Ito po yung same copy ng response ng OBP sa Notice of Suspension.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: I will now show you, counsel, JVD, I will now show you the second page of this letter, Madam Witness, being flashed on the screen.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Please look at the second page. In particular, we have what appears to be certain signatures, mga signature na nandyan sa second page ng response ng Office of the Vice President. If shown to you, Madam Witness, would you be able to identify the signatures?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: There
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: is a signature appearing on top of the name Attorney Zuleika Weka.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Attorney
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Lopez. There is a signature appearing above the name Attorney Zuleika Lopez.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Would you be able to identify that signature?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, ma'am. Yes,
Cylene May L. Del Campo: ma'am.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: There
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: is
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: another signature here appealing atop the name Lemuel Ortonio.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Please go over this signature and tell us if you are familiar. Nakikilala mo ba tong signature ng isang ortonyo sa dokumentong ito?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Why, Madam Witness?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Kasama din po ito dun sa lease ng specimen signature na nasubmit po sa amin dun sa liquidation documents nila.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And pag alam mo, sino ba itong Atty. Zuleika Lopez?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Base po dito sa dokumento na to, siya po ang Chief of Staff ng OBP.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Undersecretary po at Chief of Staff.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ito naman Mr. Lemuel Ortonio. Sino naman tong Lemuel Ortonio na to?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Base po sa document, siya po ang Assistant Secretary and Assistant Chief of Staff.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sa letter response na to, na-identify mo, may nakalagay, meron bang naka-attach dito sa letter response?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, po. Nag-attach po sila ng list of 105 activities ng Office of the Vice President for the period December 13 to 31, 2022.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: First quarter ng... Fourth
Cylene May L. Del Campo: quarter po. Fourth quarter ng 2022. Specifically, December 13 to 31, 2022.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At if we show you this list of activities na inattach sa letter response, will you be able to... identify this.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: We are flashing on the screen, Your Honor, a list of activities which is an attachment to the letter response of the OVP, Exhibit P-113B, whereat yung listahan allegedly ng mga activities ng OVP ay naka-enumerate.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Tell us, Madam Witness.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Likewise, flash on the screen. Tell us, Madam Witness, ano ang significance nitong mga list ng activities na sinubmit ng Office of the Vice President sa kanyang letter response? Anong ibig sabihin nun, list of activities?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ito po ay naging attachment nila as documents evidencing success of information gathering and or surveillance activities po na required po kapag nagkakaroon ng payment of rewards.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Anong period covered itong list of activities?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: December 13 to 31, 2022 po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And what
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: ang
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: observation eh itong activities na nakalagay dyan ay prior to the receipt of the Office of the Vice President of its Confidential Fund. Ito ba ay kinoconfirm mo?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po kasi yung Cash advance po for 2022 po is for the period December 21 to 31, 2022.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At kailan na tinanggap ang cash advance?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: December 21 po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: ang start. Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Hindi ba ang ibig sabihin ng liquidation report eh sinasabi mo kung ano yung mga pinaggamitan mo ng cash advance? Tama ba yan?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo, tama po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. And sa palagay mo?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: compliant ba to? Kasi post audit compliance ba ito?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Based po sa document na to, hindi po napakita dito na yung proof of success of the information gathering at may mga activities din po dito na from December 13. 15, 17, 18 na hindi po sakop dun sa period of utilization ng cash advance which is for December 21, 31, 2022.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So you mentioned a joint circular? Meron ka bang ano? Anong pinagbasihan mo kung bakit violation ito?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Under po kasi sa joint circular 2015-01, kapag po Ginamit ang confidential fund sa payment of rewards. Subject po ito sa tatlong conditions.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ano yung mga condition
Cylene May L. Del Campo: na iyon? First po, it should be approved by the head of agency. Pangalawa po, it should be supported with documents evidencing success of the information gathering. and or surveillance activities on account of the information given by the informer. And yung last po is it should be directly related sa confidential activities ng agency po. Okay,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: so ano dyan sa requirements ang sinasabi mo hindi sinunod ng Office of the Vice President?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ito po kasing listahan na to sinabit nila as proof of success of information gathering to support the payment of rewards. Pero based po sa documents na to, hindi po namin nakita yung particular accomplishment.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Nakakalagay sa dokumento. Examples ng activities ng Office of the Vice President for the Confidential Funds.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Pakibasa nga for the record, no? Kasi tama ba yung basa namin? May three-planting, give-giving. Please read for the record, Madam Witness. Ano yung sinasabing pinaggamitan ng confidential funds?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Dito po sa December 13, 2022, Department of Education, 2022, Partners Appreciation Night in Mandaluyong City, Metro Manila, December 15... Ah, sandali.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Appreciation Night. Opo. Sa pagkaintindi mo, confidential activity ba yan? O nasa listahan ba yan ng confidential activities base sa Joint Circular?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Based po dun sa enumeration kung saan gagamitin ang Confidential Fund, hindi po ito nakasama doon.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Basahin mo pa yung iba. So hindi. Ano pa yung iba?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: December 15, 2022, Knights of Rizal Supreme Council, 60th year of the Institute in Baguio City, Youth Campaign on Patriotism.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Meron din po...
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Compliant ba to sa listahan?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Based po sa Joint Circular, hindi po ito nakasama dun sa mga activities po. under 4.8 kung saan puwedeng gamitin ng confidential funds.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Pasahin mo nga lahat ng activities na yan for the record at sabihin mo kung compliant ito. Kung ito ba mga activities ay pinapayagan bilang liquidation ng confidential funds.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Meron po dito December 17, 2022, Christmas activity in Happy Land, Tondo, Manila. Christmas activity and exploration meeting of Extension Office Barangay 101 in Tondo, Manila. Consultation with Barangay Chairman ng Manila in Manila. Pasasalamat and update meeting TODA in Barangay Batasan Hills, Quezon City.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: May mga tree planting po, distribution of wheelchairs, gift giving, medical mission, at iba pong activities ng mga satellite offices po ng Office of the Vice President.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sa joint circular na minention mo, can you remind us ano ba talaga ang definition ng confidential funds?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ang confidential fund po, ito po yung lump sum amount na nasa General Appropriations Act na gagamitin po for confidential activities po ng isang ahensya.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At itong binasa mo, tree planting, Christmas, napakadaming Christmas party, napakadaming award ceremony, yan ba ay pinapayagan sa sinabi mong definition ng confidential funds?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Hindi po.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: With the indulgence of counsel, Miss Aileen, maliban sa hindi pinapayagan o pasok sa pwedeng paggastusan ng confidential funds yung mga binasa po ninyo, yung gastos ay ginawa rin bago na-encash yung cheque.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Kung based po sa document na ito, meron po kasing activities. dito na from December 13 to 18 na hindi po sakop dun sa period of utilization based sa
Cylene May L. Del Campo: accomplishment report. So hindi posibleng gamitin yung perang na-release ng 21 para i-reimburse yun kung tama man yung pinag-gastusan.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po, kasi under the joint circular po, meron pong portion doon na hindi po pwedeng gamitin for reimbursement yung pondo ng confidential.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So prospectively lang. So yung mga activities na pwede lang ay 21 to 31.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo, tama po.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You may proceed, counsel.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Dahil dito sa sinabi mong violation, wala sa period, no? As observed by the honorable presiding officer. At Dahil wala naman sa listahan sa Joint Circular kung saan pwedeng gamitin ng confidential funds. Ano ang ginawa mo after that, if any?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: After po evaluating the response ng OBP at saka po yung mga attachments neto, ako po ay nag-draft ng notice of disallowance at isinabit ko po ito sa aking division chief for her review.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: If I will show you, pag pinakita sa'yo ang isang notice of disallowance for purposes of the record, Your Honor, this has been premarked as Exhibit P-1-13-C. Would you be able to identify it?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Showing to you, Attorney Delacruz will show it to you. Please go over this document and tell us if the relationship of this document to the notice of disallowance you have mentioned. And again, we are seeking permission to flash it for ECC reference on screen.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo, yun po yung same copy ng notice of disallowance na in-issue namin sa Office of the Vice President.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Please look, counsel, please look at this notice of disallowance. There is a signature there on top of the name Nilda B. Plaras. Kanina pong signature ito?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Si Assistant Commissioner Nilda Plaras po ang officer in charge ng ICVAW noong ma-issue po ang dokumento na ito.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Anong ibig sabihin pag pinirmahan ng isang Assistant Commissioner ang isang Notice of Disallowance na drinak mo?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ito po is for release na po sa, na-approve po niya ang laman neto at for release na po ito sa agency. for release ng agency.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Tell us, Madam Witness, itong Notice of Disallowance ng COA-ICFAW, yung recommendation mo at yung in-approve ng Assistant Commissioner for Release, magkano? Magkano ang disallowed ng COA-ICFAW?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ang disallowance po is 73,287,000.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ano naman ang basis ng disallowance na to? Ang
Cylene May L. Del Campo: disallowance po na to, binubuo po ito ng first, yung payment of rewards in the total amount of 69,787,000.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Before you proceed, Your Honor, please, this is being flashed on the screen. This is the first page of Exhibit P-1-13-C, which is the notice of disallowance identified by this witness. First page dyan, Madam Witness, ano ang breakdown or basihan? ng iyong notice of disallowance.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yung 73,287,000 ang bumubuo po dito is yung payment for rewards amounting to 69,787,000 plus yung 3.5 million for payments for tables and chairs, desktop computers, and printers po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Dalawa ang amount na naka-indicate dyan. Bakit dalawang amount? Paki-explain.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ito po ba yung sa number 1, na yung 69, 587, at yung sa... In
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: number 1, in item number 1, if you can check your document on the screen, item number 1, sa notice of disallowance, dalawa ang amount na nakastate. Isa... 69,587,000 at yung isa ay 69,787,000. Ito ba ay typo discrepance? Ano ang bakit may hindi pareho itong amount?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ito po ay isang typographical error po. Ang tamang amount po is 69,787,000.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Ngayon naman, Madam Witness, let us go to page 2. Item number 2. Ano naman? Pakibasa ang sinabi dito sa page 2, item number 2.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Chart. The notice of disallowance po is issued kasi yung pangalawang reason po is charging payment for tables and chairs, desktop computers and printers in the total amount of 3.5 million to confidential fund without specifying that they were intended for the confidential operations slash activities undertaken by the OBP, non-compliant with the requirement of item 4.8.4 of the Joint Circular.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ano yung item 4.8? ng circular na sinasabi mo.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Pwede po ba akong mag-refer para po sa joint circular? With your permission.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Witness may refer to the document.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Thank you po.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Based po sa item 4.8.4 ng joint circular, purchase or rental of supplies, materials, and equipment for confidential operations that cannot be done through regular procedures without compromising the information gathering activity concern.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Bakit ito ay naging basihan ng disallowance? Noong tables and chairs na yan, hindi ba confidential yun? Kung saan binili yung table and chair na yan, hindi ba confidential yun, Madam Witness?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Hindi po kasi nila in-specify na the payments for table, yung tables and chairs and desktop computers were used for confidential operations po. Wala po silang nasubmit na any explanation dun sa response po nila.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Kailangan ba mag-submit ng... Anong mga kailangan i-submit na dokumento by way of para explain kung saan ginamit itong tables and chairs, laptop, tsaka anong hinahanap ninyo sa post-audit?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Dapat po mapatunayan nila na ito ay binili para po sa confidential operations ng ahensya.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At anong kailangan na dokumento?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And
Cylene May L. Del Campo: since this pertains po sa as Purchases, dapat po supported ito ng either sales invoice or official receipts po. Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sa pag-evaluate mo nitong dokumentong sinubmit ng Office of the Vice President, meron ba yun mga official receipts, sales invoice na sinubmit?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Wala po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Isa, dalawa, tatlo. Walang sinubmit, Madam Witness?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Wala pong mga resibo po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Now, Based sa inyong audit, sino-sino ang liable persons dito sa connection, in connection, in connection with this Notice of Disallowance na binasa mo? Sino-sino ang mga persons na responsible or accountable dyan sa pinakita mo?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ang
Cylene May L. Del Campo: mga persons po na liable or responsible is First po, the Head of Agency, Vice President, Sara Duterte, the Special Disbursing Officer, si Ms. Gina Acosta, at ang Chief Accountant po, na si Ms. Julieta Villia de la Rey.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Sa document na yan, pwede bang pakita mo yung mga pangalan na sinabi mo?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Nasa page 2 po. Showing to you page 2,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Madam Witness, and being flashed on the screen. Please tell us. If these are the very same persons na sinabi mo na accountable? Yes po. Bakit sila accountable?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Unang-una po, yung si Vice President Sara Duterte po, siya po ang nag-approve ng transaction and including the utilization of the cash advance.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Saan nakalagay dyan na siya ang nag-approve?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yun pong sa accomplishment report.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: and then kay Ms. Gina Acosta naman po dahil siya ang special disbursing officer and she disbursed po the cash advance.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ito namang Villa Del Rey. Bakit sinasabi mo na accountable officer siya?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Nag-certify po siya dun sa backseat ng liquidation report na ang supporting documents are complete and proper.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Hindi ba nila ginawa ito? Yung mga sinasabi mo na kailangan sa Joint Circular?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes. It kasi po yung participation nila sa transaction, kaya po sila nasama sa persons na liable po sa transaction na ito. Dahil first, si BP Sara bilang siya ang head of agency at siya po ang nag-approve ng transaction and utilization ng cash advance. Pangalawa po, ang naging participation po ni Ms. Gina Acosta is siya po ang special disbursing officer. At siya
Cylene May L. Del Campo: po
Cylene May L. Del Campo: yung nag-disburse ng cash advance. At kay Ms. Solieta Villa-Deloray naman po, sinertify niya na complete and proper yung supporting documents, pero hindi po complete and proper yung nasubmit po sa amin.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Madam Witness, nag-issue ka, nag-issue ang COA-ICFAO ng Notice of Disallowance. What happened next, if any, kung maalala mo?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Noon pong February 5, 2025, nag-appeal po ang Office of the Vice President. Nag-file po sila ng Petition for Review sa Commission proper.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And do you know what happened to this Petition for Review?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Noong April 10, 2026 po, naglabas ng decision ng commission proper at na-furnishan po ang aming office and inaffirm po nila yung notice of disallowance in the total amount of 73,287,000.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So yung petition for review, eh, disallowed pa rin.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: noon pong lumabas yung decision ng commission proper, inaffirm po nila yung disallowance.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Magkano yung disallowed ng commission proper?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Same po sa nasa notice of disallowance namin, 73,287,000 po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At ano naman ang ibig sabihin ng disallowed?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ang notice of disallowed po is sa level ni ICFO po kasi pag nag- issue kami ng notice of disallowance, meron na po silang, we demand them to ibalik po yung pondo, pero meron pong remedy, which is yung ginawa nila, nag-file sila ng petition for review po sa commission proper.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At ano naman ang nangyari sa petition for review na yan?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ayun nga po, nagkaroon ng COA decision na inaffirm po nila yung notice of disallowance.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Pagkatapos na inaffirm yung notice of disallowance ng commission, ano ang ginawa?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: If at all.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Noong May po, May, May 2026, meron po silang finial na motion for reconsideration.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So nag-file ng motion for reconsideration ang office of the Vice President. Anong nangyari sa motion for reconsideration na finial tungkol dito sa decision na ibalik ang 73 million na yan? Ano ang status?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Wala pa pong naging decision ang commission proper po. Pending resolution po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Punta naman tayo sa first quarter and second quarter of 2023 which covers the Office of the Vice President's Liquidation of Confidential Funds. What is your participation? Ano naman ang participation mo dito? pag-evaluate ng liquidation expenses or documents na sinabit ng Office of the Vice President.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: For anong period po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: For the first quarter of 2020, first and second quarters of 2023.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ako po ang nag-evaluate ng response ng OBP sa audit observation memorandum po na na-issue sa kanila for that period.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: yung dalang quarters e nag-issue ng Audit Observation Memorandum. Sinong nag-issue?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yun po, si Mr. Wamil po. Na-issue po yung AOM na yun noong time ni Mr. Wamil.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And if shown to you, this AOM, Audit Observation Memorandum, dated February 2024. For the record, this is Exhibit P-1-13-E. being shown to the witness and being flashed on the screen for easy reference. Will you be able, Madam Witness, to
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: identify the same? For the record, this is a stipulated document.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Pagkatapos ng issuance nitong Audit Observation Memorandum, meron bang ginawa ang Office of the Vice President?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Nagsubmit po sila ng response noong April 19, 2024.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Para saan itong response?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Response po nila sa AOM na na-issue po sa kanila for the first and second quarters of 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And just to remind us, anong period covered ng first quarter?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: It's for February 6 to March 29, 2023. At yung second quarter po, April 25 to June 30, 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: How many, Madam Witness, kung maalala mo, ilang, ano, ano ah, wait, I will withdraw the question. Ito ba sa response na sinubmit ng Office of the Vice President, ano ang mga naka-attach dito sa response na to?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Sa response po nila, nag-attach po sila ng acknowledgement receipts, certification ni Colonel La Chica, at mga protective intelligence operations reports po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Before we go to those documents na sinasabi mo, sa response being shown on the screen, there is on the second page, counsel, will you show the second page? There is a second page, there is a signature appearing on the second page of the response.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Whose signature is that, appearing above the name, Attorney Lopez?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Kaninong signature yan, if you know?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Kay Atty. Zuleika Lopez po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At dito naman, above the name, Mr. Ortonio?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Kay Mr. Limuel Ortonio po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And you are familiar with these signatures for the same reason she stated earlier?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po, tama po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sa response na sinubmit. ng Office of the Vice President, sinabi mo kanina meron mga acknowledgement receipts, no? If shown to you, a summary, these acknowledgement receipts, how many acknowledgement receipts were attached to the response for the first quarter of 2023?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yung sa first quarter po ng 2023 is 519.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: 519 acknowledgement receipts. At sinabi mo kanina, discoveries of period February 6 to March 29, 2023. Tama?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo, tama po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sa second quarter of 2023,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: ilan naman ang acknowledgement receipts nang sinubmit ng Office of the Vice President?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: 530 po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Total number ng acknowledgement receipts for the first quarter and second quarter is how much?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: 1,049 po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At Madam Witness, if shown to you these acknowledgement receipts or a summary,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: if
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: shown to you certified through copies of these acknowledgement receipts, would you be able to identify the same?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: By agreement with the Honorable Presiding Officer, Your Honor, in lieu of this witness glossing over or looking over the documents, but they are in front of her, Your Honor, we manifest that she has prepared a tabulation.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, as agreed to also by counsel for the respondent, the witness need not peruse individually and flip over as the word used by counsel. These ARs, I may refer to her tabulation and her summary that she prepared with respect to Ma'am Cylene, the first and second quarter of 2022 for the ARs, acknowledgement receipts, for the Office of the Vice President. You may refer to your table and her summary, Ma'am, if you have one.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, please may we also make the manifestation, Your Honor, for future witnesses, Your Honor. This should not... They should not dispense with our future witnesses being able to identify, to use and to identify certain acknowledgement receipts, Your Honor, which are part of the summary or tabulation.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Without prejudice, the reservation of counsel, the court will allow it. Ms. Aileen or Atty. Lorna, can you kindly give us a copy because that is not yet a marked document, right?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, for the record,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: That is not the pre-marked document, rather.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The table.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: This summary, Your Honor, hindi po ito pre-marked, but we are now giving a copy to the honorable presiding officer and to counsel for the respondent.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, kindly do so.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The clerk of court is instructed to reproduce the copy to be able to give each senator-judge with
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: A copy of the table or summary.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: For the record, Your Honor, while our witness is perusing this document, we have given a copy of what she is going over, both to the presiding officer, through the Clerk of Court, Your Honor, and to the Respondents' Council.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And again, for the record, this is for the first quarter, February 6, March 29, 2023, consisting of 519 documents in that summary, and second quarter of the Office of the Vice President, covering the period April 25 to June 30, 2023, consisting of 1,049 documents, Your Honor, total for both quarters.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: and Your Honor, we
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: will be requesting through the Clerk of Court, Your Honor, at some time, that this be marked as exhibit,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: no,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: no, the tabulation being identified by the witness be identified for the first quarter as P-1-30-Q-1 and series.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: tabulation for the second quarter be marked as Exhibit P-1-31-Q and Series, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The aforementioned tabulations and their summaries are hereby ordered to be so marked by the Clerk of Court at the appropriate time.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: We have selected for
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: the first and second quarter, Your Honor, we have selected for better appreciation of the honorable presiding judge and our senator-judges, Your Honor. We have selected certain acknowledgement receipts which we request be shown to the witness when
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: she is
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: done.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Madam Witness, just look at the summaries, please.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: You confirm that these summaries marked in evidence now are yours?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Now, tell us, walk us through, anong proseso ang ginawa mo sa paggawa mo ng mga summary na to?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: During the evaluation po, I tabulated po yung acknowledgement receipts, dun po, based sa date, kung kailan sila na-execute, the expense, and the amount po. Kaya, ang nakalagay po sa tabulation ko is the date, the amount, and the expense po. Hindi na po namin na, hindi ko na po na tabulate yung sa names.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yung pangalan? Okay, so nakalagay dyan yung amount, yung date, and yung expense. At yung expense. But if I show to you certain acknowledgement receipts which were part of the documents that you said were turned over to the COA ICFAO office, would you be able, pag pinakita sa'yo certain acknowledgement receipts na parte? na nasa part ng tabulation o summary mo, would you be able to identify the same?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: show you now. And with the kind permission of this honorable court, we have chosen certain acknowledgement receipts to be flashed on the screen, Your Honor, and being shown to the witness.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Marked as Exhibit P-1-8-1418 is a certain... What is that? It's a certain Pia Piatos Lim.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Could you read the date, Madam Witness?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Dito po is May 17,
Cylene May L. Del Campo: 2023, na-receive po ni Pia Piatos Lim.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Para saan ito, allegedly?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: For the purchase
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: of information po. And may signature dyan sa ilalim. Whose signature is this?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: signature is this?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: At the bottom. Ito po is signature po ng admin staff namin sa ICFAO.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Who is your admin staff in ICFAO?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Si Mr.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: David E. Bacay po. David Bacay. David E. Bacay. And that is his signature, administrative. Ano ang significance nitong sinayin ng administrative staff ninyo, ang acknowledgement receipts?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Pinapatunayan po nitong certification neto na ito po yung copy na sinubmit sa amin ng OBP. Pinapatunayan
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: nala na ang binabasa mo ay kasama sa binigay ng respondent.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po, kasama po ito sa binigay sa amin na acknowledgement receipt in response po sa AOM.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So yung summary ng acknowledgement
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: receipts for the first quarter?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: and second quarter ng Office of the Vice President consisting of 1,049 separate acknowledgement receipts. Sabihin mo nga sa amin kung meron similar signature ang all
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: other acknowledgement receipts ni Mr. Davin Bacay.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, Paul. Dun po sa mga acknowledgement receipts na ito is lahat po sinertify ni Mr. Bacay na ito po ay mga kopya ng acknowledgement receipts na sinubmit po sa amin ng OBP. Punta
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: naman tayo sa P-1-8-1483. Pangalan ng, please read for the record.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Acknowledgement receipt. This is to acknowledge receipt of the amount of P150,000 for the purchase of information received by Ralph Josh Bacon on June 20, 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Bacon. Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Alas 12 na, gutom na tayo. Yung susunod na pangalan mukhang P -1-8-928.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Pakibasa for the record.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Acknowledgement receipt. This is to acknowledge receipt of the amount of 50,000 pesos for the purchase of information received by Ann Ong Pauko, date March 20, 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay, next. P-1-8-1015. Pangalan ni Hart. Hart Santiago. Pakibasa.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Bumili siya ng supplies. This is to acknowledge receipt of the amount of 250,000 pesos for the purchase or rental of supplies, materials and equipment for confidential operations. Open and close parenthesis, payment for the purchase of supplies received by Hart Santiago, date Feb 27, 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: kung sino ito at kung related sila sa presiding officer natin? Hindi po. Hindi naman. Bakit hindi? Bakit hindi ka nag-verify ng mga pangalan? May pagkain na bacon, may parang kamag-anak ni Hart. Why did you not verify the names in this 1049?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Acknowledgement receipts.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Sa ICFO po kasi ang ginagawa namin is compliance audit po. Anong ibig sabihin nun? I-chinecheck po namin kung compliant ba sa Joint Circular at kompleto at proper ba yung mga liquidation documents po na sinasubmit sa amin in relation po sa provisions ng Joint Circular. Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sinabi mo kung proper ba. Ito bang payment of purchase of supplies? Proper ba yan sa paggamit ng confidential funds?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yung payment for supplies po, kasama po siya dun sa enumeration kapag payment for supplies na ginamit po sa confidential operations. At
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: sinabi mo earlier, dapat yung mga sinasubmit, may kasamang sales invoice at mga kasamang purchase documents. Meron bang kasama? Dito sinubmit ni Ms. Hart?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Wala po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: P-1-8-1807, Fiona Villegas. Pakibasa.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Acknowledgement receipt. This is to acknowledge receipt of the amount of 500,000 for the purchase or rental of supplies, materials, and equipment for confidential operations. Open and close parentheses. Purchase of provision of medical and food aid.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Nakalagay purchase of medical and food aid. Ito ba isang ayon sa pinapayagan na paggamitan ng confidential funds?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Base po dito, nakalagay po na it's for the purchase of supplies na naka-open and close po, provision of medical and food aid. P-1-8,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: 1466, kamag-anak ata to ni Senator Bong Revilla. Beth Revilla, 50,000, purchase of information. Ang purchase of information ba ay allowed, allowable expense?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po, under 4.8.1 po, kasama po ang purchase of information.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Kung kasama, bakit mo dinisallow itong purchase of information?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Hindi po ito kasama dun sa nadisallow po. Ito? Hindi po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Balik naman tayo sa P-1-8-1220. Kamag-anak naman to ni Senator Riza Ontiveros. Clarice Ontiveros. Please
Cylene May L. Del Campo: read the amount. This is to acknowledge receipt of the amount of 500,000 for the purchase or rental of supplies, materials, and equipment for confidential operations. Open and close parenthesis, purchase of provision of medical and food aid. At again, disallow dito. Kasama po ito dun sa na-disallow po kasi based on this acknowledgement receipt. We cannot ascertain, hindi ko po ma-ascertain if this is really nabigay for purchase of medical and food aid, kaya humingi pa po ako ng additional documents.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Nabigyan rin itong Jose Jocno, Jr.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Kamag-anak ba to ni
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: public
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: prosecutor, Madam Witness? Binerify mo ba? Can you look at P-1-8-1482? Nagbigay ng information itong Jokno,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: kapangalan Jose Jokno, Jr. Baka anak ni congressman. Hindi mo tinanong kanina nung dumaan ka dyan? Hindi po. Ito naman, 1-8, P-1-8-994. kamag-anak naman ni Senator Lapid, Diane Maple Lapid, na tumanggap ng 150,000 pesos na bumili daw ng supplies. Pakibasa for the record.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: This is to acknowledge receipt of the amount of 150,000 pesos for the purchase or rental of supplies, materials, and equipment for confidential operations.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sorry, go ahead.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Open and close parenthesis, payment for the purchase of supplies received by Diane May Paul Lapid on Feb 17, 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Bakit naman naka-disallowed itong expense na to?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Gaya po yung sa provision and medical and food aid, based on this acknowledgement receipts po, hindi po ma-assertain kung this is really given for the purchase of supplies, kaya nanghihipo ko ng additional documents po. Meron na naman.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Not once, but for the second time, Lapid family, John A. Lapid, Jr.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Acknowledgement receipt. This is to acknowledge receipt of the amount of 350,000 pesos for the purchase or rental of supplies, materials, and equipment for confidential operations.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Purchase of provision of medical and food aid. received by John A. Lapid, Jr., date May 3, 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Witness, apart from these selected acknowledgement receipts, the total for the first quarter and the second quarter of the Office of the Vice President are similar acknowledgement receipts for purchase of medical and food aid, pambili daw ng supplies, pambili ng iba-iba pa. Ano ang masasabi mo sa mga expenses na ito?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Nung in-evaluate ko po, kasama po siya dun sa naging findings ko at hinihingan ko po ng additional documentation to ascertain po na these are paid na pinambili po ng supplies at medical and food aid.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Nung sinabi mo humingi ka ng additional information or documents, nag-submit ba? ang Office of the Vice President para patunayan talaga na itong medical, grocery, etc. tables talagang ginamit sa confidential funds.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Nakasama po ito dun sa Notice of Disallowance and yung Notice of Disallowance po is within the prescribed period pa po sila para mag-comply.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Nag-comply ba sila?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Wala pa po silang naging action after ma-receive nila ito.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So despite na binigyan n'yo ng COA ng opportunity para mag-submit ng additional documents para matatunayan nila or mag-explain man lang bakit nandiyan ang mga pangalan na yan at bakit walang mga resibo na inattach para pag-liquidate. Nag-submit ba ang Office of the Vice President ng additional documents after this notice of disallowance?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Dahil nga po nabanggit ko na naging notice of disallowance po ito, ang remedy po nila is to appeal po sa commission proper. And nandun pa po sila sa period with to appeal po sa commission proper.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ngayon, what other ano? Meron pa bang ibang dokumento na sinubmit ang office of the vice president na sinama sa response nila?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: May sinabi, to support po the payment of rewards, nagsambit po sila ng certification ni Colonel Raymond Dante Pilachica together with the Protective Intelligence Operations Report.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: If shown to you, will you be able kung pakita sa'yo itong document, Exhibit P-1-12-G, isang certification dated April 4, 2024, stipulated document with the defense, Your Honor. Please identify the same. Also being flashed on the screen.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po, ito po yung certification na naka-attach sa response ng OBP.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Correction, Your Honor, it's not stipulated. What relation does this certification to the one you mentioned?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ito po yung same certification na naka-attach po sa response ng OBP.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ano naman ang significance? Bakit?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Bakit? Anong significance nitong certification na sinubmit nila?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ito po ay isinabit nila to support po the payment of rewards. Under po kasi sa Joint Circular, pag may payment of rewards, dapat po subject ito sa tatlong conditions. And kasama po yun yung documents evidencing success of the information gathering and or surveillance activities.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Nung nag-testify dito si Atty. Wamil, sinabi niya nung tinanong siya ng prosecution, ito ba ay compliant. At ang sagot niya eh, ito ay pro forma.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Copy-paste ang sinabi ng prosecution. Kinoconfirm mo ba yan na ito ay parang annex?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ito pong certification na to, hindi po ito kasama dun sa annexes sa Joint Circular. Ang sinasabi po niyang certification is yung certification ng accountable officer. Yun po yung kasama sa annexes sa Joint Circular.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So ano nga ang significance nitong certificate, if you know.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ito po yung sinubmit nila para po as proof of success of the information gathering and surveillance activities po to support the payment of rewards.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Together with this, meron rin sinubmit, earlier you mentioned, ang Office of the Vice President ng tinatawag na protective intelligence operation reports or P-I-O-R na inattach nila sa response. If shown to you, Madam Witness, will you be able to identify these P-I-O-Rs?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, po. For the first and second quarters of the Office of the Vice President.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: For the record, Your Honor, this... Protective Intelligence Operations Reports or PIRs have been marked in exhibit pre-marked as P-1-12-H up to P-1-12-H-9 and exhibits P-1-12-M-1.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: up to P-12-M-13 for the prosecution. Which for
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the record is 1-115 OVPN series for the respondent. Correct, Attorney Christine?
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Please proceed, counsel.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Thank you, Madam Witness. As
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: correctly noted by the presiding officer, Your Honor, although this witness is taking time, these are also
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: pre-marked documents of the defense, Your Honor, although they, again, refused to stipulate on the same.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Permission to sit down, Your Honor?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Sure, Attorney Lorna.
Presiding officer: While we
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: are waiting, Chair would like to inform the senator-judges and the parties that we will be pausing for lunch break at 12, regardless of where we are, since clearly... We might not be able to finish with the direct before 12. So kung saan man tayo abutan, hanggang dun lang din po tayo. And we'll continue after lunch.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, we will be able to finish before lunchtime with the Office of the Vice President.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: But
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: not with the witness, counsel.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Not with the witness. And after lunch, Your Honor, with the deputy.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Because of
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the...
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Atty. Christine, you can also sit down if you want to.
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: Thank you, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Atty. Lorna, next time you can provide either a high chair for you so that you can sit while...
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: I think the office of the clerk misunderstood. I asked for a high chair. They gave me a high podium, Your Honor. The clerk of court is
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: so directed. I think it's more convenient to have a high chair.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yes, Your Honor. Thank you.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: I'd rather call it a high chair, Atty. Kapunan, than a bar stool.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: With your respect, Your Honor, I'm more familiar with bar schools. I
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: would know. I would have thought, counsel.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, Ms. Aileen. Are you just about done, ma'am?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, po, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Are you ready, Ms. Aileen?
Presiding officer: Attorney Lorna, you
Presiding officer: may proceed.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: With the permission of this honorable court. Thank you, Madam Witness. You have gone over fires
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: or... protective intelligence operations reports which were attached to the Office of the Vice President's response for the first and second quarter of 2023. Madam Witness, sa tinignan mong reports na yan at na-evaluate mo na reports na yan, ano ang mga observation mo?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Doon po sa protective intelligence operations reports, ito po ay inattach nila kasama yung certification as documents evidencing success. And based po sa aking evaluation ng mga PIORs, ang nakalagay po rito is ang date and locations ng mga engagement ng vice presidents kasama na din po yung mga satellite offices nila. Nakalagay din po dito yung probable threats doon sa mga activities na ito, pati na rin
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Magmula sa planning stage, actual operation, and post-operation. Pero during the evaluation po ng documents na ito, hindi ko po nakita yung particular accomplishments po na magwawarant sa payment of rewards. Bakit sinabi
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: mo na napakahaba ng mga dokumentong to? Bakit sinabi mo nung na-evaluate mo ay hindi mo nakita yung hinahanap mo o yung kailangan? kasama nito sa mga dokumentong ito. Bakit, Madam Witness?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Under po kasi sa Joint Circular, yun nga po, sa payment of rewards, it should be supported with documents evidencing success. Pero based po sa mga documents na ito, ang nakalagay lang po dun sa certification is a general statement that there were no untoward incidents dun sa mga engagement ng Office of the Vice President together with the implementation ng programs. Pero hindi po ito naging sapat.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ano-ano itong mga programs na sinasabi nila na pinaggamitan ng confidential funds? Wala ka bang nakita dito sa mga sinubmit na kadami-daming mga dokumento? Anong specifics nitong activities allegedly na pinaggamitan?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: May mga activities po sa mga meetings, mga attendance po sa mga festival, ganun po. Tsaka yung mga engagement din po ng satellite offices.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Hindi ba qualified ito? Hindi ba allowed ito? Yung mga nagmi-meeting, nagmi-meeting-meeting. Paano mo manalaman? How can you ascertain that these meetings are not, are indeed to discuss? Confidential activities.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Kasi po, ang nakalagay lang po doon is kung ano yung mga activity na inatendan doon po ng Vice President. Kasama na rin po yung mga programs ng mga satellite offices niya, pati po yung libreng sakay program ng OBP. Libreng sakay
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: program?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo, kasama po doon sa PIORs.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Hindi ba ito confidential?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yung
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: libre na sakay na yan?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ano
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: pa yung mga activities ng satellite offices na sinasabi mo na hindi naman tamang paggamit ng confidential funds?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: activity nila is provided rice box to Mursha fire victims. Sandali.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Rice box to Mursha
Cylene May L. Del Campo: fire victims.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Baka confidential ang rice victims na yan, Madam Witness.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Tapos, tupad beneficiaries at BCNHS. Can you speak to the
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: mic, please?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Tupad beneficiaries at BCNHS Gym, Dole, Tupad payout May 1, 2023, 198 recipients, daily wage for 50, a total of 841 cash disbursed 10 days.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Mga tupad beneficiaries, linis na dyan, kung magkano.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ito po yung mga naging activity po dun sa bakulog
Cylene May L. Del Campo: natin.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: So, rice giving,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: tupad
Cylene May L. Del Campo: activities,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: ano pa?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Medical mission po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Medical mission.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: release of rice boxes to beneficiaries in Sebaste and Pique, visited MAIPP hospitals and provided GLs at billing accounting offices to get a copy of SOA.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: With
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the indulgence of counsel, Ms. Aileen, these are the activities na sinasabi nilang kinovern ng intelligence operations.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ito po yung inattach nila as proof of success of the information gathering.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Ng activities nga.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Not that ginamit yung confidential fund sa pagbigay ng bigas. Not that ginamit yung confidential fund sa pagbigay ng tupad. Not that ginamit yung confidential fund sa maip.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo. Bale po, ito yung naging activities ng Vice President po. Pero
Cylene May L. Del Campo: hindi po
Cylene May L. Del Campo: yung confidential fund yung ginamit dito.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Na naging ligtas siya. Ika nga. Opo. Parang conducted surveillance
Cylene May L. Del Campo: activities po. sa mga programang ito. Okay.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You may proceed, counsel.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Again, para
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: sa record, itong mga activities daw, yung mga rice giving, yung mga tupad na yan, doon siya nag-conduct ng surveillance activities? Yun ba ang sinasabi mo, Madam Witness?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ang nakalagay po kasi doon sa certification, nag-conduct siya ng confidential surveillance activities. Before, parang ang pagkakaintindi ko po dito is yung nag-conduct sila ng surveillance activities before the engagement of the Vice President. At
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: sinabi mo na kasama to sa notice of disallowance?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo, kasi hindi napapakita ng mga dokumentong ito kasama yung certification na there was success in the information gathering and surveillance activities kasi yung statement lang po is there were no untoward incidents. Hinahanap ko po kung ano yung...
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Pag sinabing, Madam Witness, pag sinabing there were no untoward incidences, hindi ba evidence of success yun? Walang yung mga komunista, yung mga terorista. Imbis na nag-away-away, tumanggap na lang ng rice pack, tumanggap na lang ng tupad. Hindi ba success yun? Hindi sila nag-away-away?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ang hinahanap ko po kasi dito, sample po dun sa isang activity is, nakalagay probable threat, CTG, parang ganun, NFPA po. Ang hinahanap po kasi is payment of rewards. Meron bang dun sa probable threat na yun, may nahuli ba? Parang ganun po. Yun ang mag-warrant ng payment of rewards po. At wala
Cylene May L. Del Campo: kang ganun na
Cylene May L. Del Campo: nakita sa
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: evaluation mo, Madam Witness. Opo. Going now to the third quarter of 2023, covering the period July 14. to September 30, 2023. Anong participation mo, if any, Madam Witness, dito sa pag-audit ng liquidation documents na sinubmit ng Office of the Vice President?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ako po ang nag-evaluate ng response nila sa audit observation for the third quarter po ng 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At Madam Witness, ano ang nangyari, if any?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Nung ma-issue po yung Audit Observation Memorandum noong August 8, 2024, nagsubmit po ang OBP ng response nila noong August 27, 2024.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: The relation of this AOM dated August 8, 2024, marked as Exhibit P
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: -1
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: -12-I
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: for the prosecution and stipulated upon in the last hearing with Defense Counsel.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: As respondents, Exhibit 1-106, LVP.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Correct, Your Honor.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: This is the same copy po of the AOM na na-issue namin sa OBP.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Now, showing to you and it's being flashed on the screen as it's being shown to you. Sa last page, pakitingin sa last page, merong signature dyan over the name Nilda Plaras.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Whose signature is this?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Si Assistant Commissioner Nilda Plaras po ang officer in charge ng ICFAO noong ma-issue po ang dokumento na ito.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Anong? Ibig sabihin na pumirma ang isang Nilda Plaras na Commissioner Associate, Assistant Commissioner ng Koa Ikpao.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ito po ay na-review at na-approve niya and is ready for release na po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ano mga ano, ano-ano, if at all, ang mga findings or issues na rinase mo na in-approve naman ng... Assistant Commissioner. Ano-ano yung mga issues na nakalagay dyan sa AOM or Audit Observation Memorandum, Madam Witness?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ang mga issues po dito sa Audit Observation Memorandum na ito is first, the submitted liquidation documents po. Wala pong naka-attach na documentary evidence of payments.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, we request permission to flash this on the screen.
Presiding officer: Counsel Medusa.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yung pangalawa naman po, yung payment of rewards na nagkakahalaga ng 35 million were not supported with documents evidencing success. Pangatlo po, yung physical and financial plan, hindi po nakaspecify yung specific confidential activities. At yung pangapat po, yung box E ng disbursement voucher kung saan makikita yung receipt of payment ng SDO ng cash advance ay hindi po napirmahan. Bakit
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: itong apat na findings na pinakita natin ngayon, bakit eh hindi compliant ito at linigayon ninyo sa notice sa AOM?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yung sa una po, under the joint circular po, dapat po ang disbursement for confidential fund should be supported with documents evidencing payments po. At? Hindi po ito naisubmit sa amin, kaya po hiningi namin sa AOM.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yung pangalawang
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: finding
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: na sinabi mo,
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yung pangalawa naman po, yung payment of rewards under the joint circular under item 4.8.5.b, it should be supported with documents evidencing success. Pero dun sa initial submission po nila, walang naka-attach na documents evidencing success to support the payment of rewards. At
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: yung pangatlong finding, bakit nasa AOM ninyo ito?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Kasi po yung sa physical and financial plan po nila, hindi nakaspecify kung ano yung confidential activities na paggagamitan na magiging basis po ng disbursement ng confidential fund. At Madam Witness,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: lastly, yung findings mo, yung pang-apat. Bakit sinasabi n'yo na... Bakit sinama to sa audit observation memorandum?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yung box e po kasi ng disbursement voucher kung saan pumipirma yung SDO pag na-receive na nga yung cheque is wala pong pirma yung special disbursing officer.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: After
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: you issued this AOM, anong ginawa if any ng Office of the Vice President?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: After po nilang mag... After nilang ma-receive itong Audit Observation Memorandum, nag-submit po sila ng response noong August 27, 2024.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And if shown to you, pag pinakita sa iyo itong response dated August 27, 2024, would you be able to identify the same?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Honor, please, witness is looking at Exhibit P-1-12-J.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Again, despite this being the response of the Vice President herself, Council for Defense did not stipulate on this document.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: But they marked it as Exhibit 1-116, OVPN Series, correct, counsel?
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: Correct, Your
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Honor. Proceed, counsel.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Who signed this response, if you know?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Si Atty. Zuleika T. Lopez at si Mr. Limuel G. Ortonio po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Again, Madam Witness, you are familiar with these signatures for the same reason you stated?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po. Kasama po ito dun sa specimen signatures na naka-attach po sa liquidation documents.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Dito sa response ng Office of the Vice President, meron bang mga dokumento na sinama dito sa response na to? Yes po. Ano-ano itong mga documents?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Nagsubmit po sila ng acknowledgement receipts as documents evidencing payments. Tapos, to support po the payment of rewards, nagsubmit sila ng
Cylene May L. Del Campo: certification ni Colonel Raymond Dante Pilachica together with the Protective Intelligence Operations Report. At yung panghuli pong attachment ay yung warrant register. Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: By agreement and upon direction of the presiding officer, we will be marking instead the tabulation. For the period July 14th to September 30th, 2023, representing the third quarter liquidation, alleged liquidation expense.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Without, of course, without prejudice to the right to our opportunity to present them at the appropriate time separately to the appropriate witnesses in the future, Your Honor.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Madam Witness,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: if you are shown acknowledgement receipts, would
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: you be able
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: to identify them?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: We will not show them now, but did you prepare, if at all, tabulation or summary of these acknowledgement receipts for the third quarter?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, po. Yes, po. Meron po akong tabulation.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Would you please show them to us?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: We have copies, Your Honor, of these tabulations or summaries. And for the record, we're giving the Honorable Presiding Officer and
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: counsel for the respondent, copy of the summaries.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Madam
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Witness, these summaries that you prepared, tell us the process involved. Ano-anong ginawa mo? Paano ka nakarating sa mga tabulation o summary na yan?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Nung ma-receive ko po yung documents na sinubmit kasama po ng response, In-encode ko po yung mga acknowledgement receipts na naglalaman po ng disbursement nila by date, activity, and the amount po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: we have selected a few of these acknowledgement receipts.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: If shown to you, please identify the same. P-1 being flashed on the screen.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Pakibasa nga ng mga pangalan dito.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Acknowledgement receipts. This is to acknowledge receipt of the amount of 130,000 pesos for the purchase of information received by name Beverly Claire Pampano, date September 9, 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: This is P-1-8-2051 in the name of Pampano. P-1-8-2107, queso naman ito, queso. Please read.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: English cheese, Matthew N. Queso, 7, 1523, magkano to, Madam Witness?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: 250,000 po at nareceived ni Matthew N. Queso noong July 15, 2023. Ginamit for payment of supplies.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Susunod, Nova Santos, 50,000 pesos, P-1-8-2147, payment on for the purchase of supplies. At another one, P-1-8-2195 sa isang sala Kasim, 8-11-2023 for 180,000 pesos. Itong payment of supplies na pinakita natin, ito ba ay allowable expense ng confidential
Cylene May L. Del Campo: funds? Yes po, under 4.8.4 of the Joint Circular po. purchase of
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: supplies, is this compliant with the Joint Circular?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yun po, yung sa purchase of supplies, based on the acknowledgement receipt po na ito, hindi ko ma-assertain na talagang pinambili siya ng supplies, kaya humingi po ako ng additional documentation.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So, sa nilagay sa acknowledgement receipt, purchase of supplies, hindi naman in-explain saan binili yung supply.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Wala po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Wala din.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Nakalagay lang po dito na for confidential operations.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Lahat ng sinabi, no? At yung mga sinasabi ditong payment of supplies pa. Kagaya nitong, okay, P-1-8-1933, Renan Piatos, purchase of information naman to. P-1-8, 2258, Xiaomi,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Xiaomi, Xiaomi, Ocho, 100,000 pesos, purchase of supplies, another one, P-1-18-2092, flash on the screen, sa isang J. Camote,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: 200,000, payment of purchase of supplies, 8-11-2023, At itong manga, gumawa ata ko ng mint, fruit salad ito, may kamote, may manga, may keso, P-1-8-2262, Migi Mango, for 50,000 pesos.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Anong masasabi mo dito, Madam Witness?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yung mga acknowledgement receipts po na purchase of supplies, hiningan ko po ng additional documentation to ascertain po na ipinabili po talaga ito ng supplies.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Bumili daw siya ng information. Last three, last four in this list. P-1-A-2635 for Contis, Connor Adrian, 9-20-2023 for 50,000. Reward payment, P-18-2178, Hanilet Camil C., 8-3-20-23, 350,000 pesos, P-1-18-2665, Christine Applegate Estrada, 50,000 pesos for reward payment, and last but not the least, P-1-18-2010, Isang Denise Tanya Escudero, August 25, 2023. bumili ng information itong Escudero for 120,000 pesos. Madam Witness, may queso, may Escudero, may Honeylette, may Estrada. Anong observation mo dito sa mga selected ARs na pinakita sa'yo?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yung sa mga payment of rewards po, hindi po siya supported ng documents evidencing success. And yun sa purchase of supplies po, hiningan ko po ng additional documentation to ascertain na binayad po talaga ito para sa supplies na ginamit sa confidential operations.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, please, we just have three certifications for the Office of the Vice President and then we will go to the DepEd but it's now 12 o'clock. and all with the names Apple, Queso, Manga, and etc. I think it is time for us to have lunch, Your Honor.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: With the permission of this Honorable Court.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Of course, Counsel. If you think it is a good time to pause so that your direct examination may not be cut at an inappropriate time, Chair will accede to that.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: May we ask that the witness be temporarily excused, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The witness is excused for lunch. Kain ka muna, Ma'am Cylene. We resume at 12.30. Chair declares a lunch recess.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Miss Aileen, still testifying under the same oath, ma'am?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, po, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Attorney Lorna, you may proceed with the continuation of your direct. When you're ready.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: With the permission of the Honorable Court. Madam Witness?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Good afternoon, Madam Witness. Good
Cylene May L. Del Campo: afternoon, po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Before we ended the morning proceedings, you identified acknowledgement receipts, ma'am.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Maliban dito sa mga acknowledgement receipts, what other documents were attached to the Office of the Vice President's response, if any?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: To support po the payment of rewards, nag-attach po sila ng certification from Colonel Dante Pilachica and the Protective Intelligence Operation Reports for the third quarter of 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: If shown to you these certifications na minensyon mo, will you be able to identify the same?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay, showing to you, Madam Witness, certification dated September 30, 2023, pre-marked as Exhibit P-1-12-K. Also being shown on the screen, with the kind permission of this Honorable Presiding Officer.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: What relation does this certification have sa sinabi mong inattach sa response ng office ng Vice President?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: This is the same copy po ng certification attached to their response.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ano naman ang observation or significance nitong certification?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ito po ay inattach nila to support the payment of rewards. Under the Joint Circular po kasi, if it is for payment of rewards, it should be supported with documents evidencing success. And based on this document po, hindi ko po nakita yung particular accomplishment that will warrant the payment of rewards.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So itong certification na in-identify mo, compliant ito sa Joint Circular na pinagbasihan mo ng evaluation?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Hindi po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sinabi mo walang supporting documents, evidencing success. Ano ba dapat ang mga dokumentong supporting success ng operations?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Based po sa Joint Circular, wala pong in-identify doon. Ang sinabi lang is documents evidencing success. Pero based po sa evaluation ko dito sa dokumento na to, hindi ko po nakita yung particular accomplishment na proof of success po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Also, earlier, sinabi mo na together with the Vice President's response, meron siyang inattached na tinatawag na Protective Intelligence Operations Reports. Tama?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo, tama po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: P-I-O-R, Protective Intelligence Operations Report, would you be able to identify them?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Showing to you, Madam Witness. What was marked? What was pre-marked as exhibits P-1-12-L up to P-1-12-L-10, tell this honorable court.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: If
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: these are the certifications on
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: the protective intelligence operation report that you mentioned.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Likewise, with the permission of the presiding officer being flashed on the screen for easy reference of the impeachment court.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Will the tech kindly check kung saan ang gagaling yung ingay na iyon? For
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the record, witnesses perusing I presume counsel, exhibit P-1-12-1-1 up to P-1-12-1-10. The PIOR of the engagements of the Vice President, as well as the certification dated September 30, 2023, Exhibit P-1-12-K, respectively, Respondents Exhibit 1-116-OVP and Series. We
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: would also like to manifest for the record, Your Honor, that despite this being prosecution's exhibits, and Mark as well, separately, as defense exhibits, these being documents submitted to the COA ICFAO, Your Honor, the Office of the Vice President. Counsel for the Office of the Vice President or for the respondent refused to stipulate to these documents, Your Honor. For the record.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The Clerk of Court is directed to kindly instruct the tech to check what's wrong with the mics.
Presiding officer: And the tech is
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: He is allowed to come here to plenary to look at it if necessary.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel may proceed. I believe the witness is through perusing the documents.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Thank you. Thank
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: you, Madam Witness. Having gone over these documents, Madam Witness, P-1-12-L hanggang P-L-12-L-10. na reports ng Protective Intelligence Operations.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ano-ano ang mga engagements na nakita mo sa mga reports na to?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Dun po sa mga engagement ni Vice President, yung attendance po niya sa mga meetings, sa mga commencement exercises po. Tapos dito naman po sa mga satellite offices niya, may mga tree planting activities po, mga courtesy
Cylene May L. Del Campo: visits. and coordination meetings po. And lahat po nang naging engagement nila for the third quarters of 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yung mga nakalagay sa third quarter na report na sinabi mo, ganun din ang linagay sa first and second quarter na tinestify mo kanina?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po, may mga activities na pareho po. Mga meetings, mga attendance po sa iba-ibang events. Tree planting meetings, award
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: ceremony, etc., Madam Witness.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Sinabi mo rin kanina na hindi ito compliant sa Joint Circular. Dito sa mga sinabit na in-identify mo, compliant na ba ito sa
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Joint Circular?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Hindi pa din po naipakita sa mga dokumentong ito yung particular accomplishment na will warrant the payment of rewards.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Pero on clarification
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: of the presiding officer, Tinanong kung ano ang hindi compliant, yung pagkaroon ba ng tree planting o yung sinasabi nilang activity in connection with confidential funds. Sa tree planting na yan, anong nakikita mo na activity in connection with alleged surveillance?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yun po kasing nakalagay doon sa certification, nagkakaroon po sila ng surveillance activities. before yung mga activities na ito. Pero based po kasi sa evaluation ko, hindi po kasi napakita dito kung ano yung particular accomplishment that will warrant the payment of rewards. Gaya po sa isang activity na nakalagay nga po, ang probable threat is yung sa CTG, mga NPA, ganyan po. Hindi po makita sa mga dokumentong ito na... na itong probable threats na to, ano yung naging successful result? Meron bang nahuli sa mga ito? Ganun po yung hinahanap namin as support sa payment of rewards. Pero
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: itong sinasabi mong evidence of success, ilan ang NPA o ilan ang terorista, ilan ang komunistang nahuli? Hindi ba yan confidential information na hindi dapat nila i-divulge, Madam Witness?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Sa KOA po kasi, hinihingi po namin yun para mapatunayan talaga na naging totoo yung payment of rewards. So
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: hindi pwedeng sabihin na ay hindi napin pwedeng i-divulge kasi confidential yan. Kailangan pa rin under the joint circular na mapatunayan yung success ng panggastos ng confidential funds sa risulta na sinasabi ng nabawasan ng terorista, nabawasan ng insurgency, kailangan pa
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: rin document. Madam
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Witness?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po, para po mapatunayan yung pagbibigay ng payment of rewards.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: After itong Office of the Vice President's response in relation sa third quarter expenditure, February 6 to September 30, 2023, at saka sa first and second quarter. Ano nangyari? What happened next after all of these response of the Office of the Vice President for the three quarters?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: During po the evaluation ng responses sa dalawang AOM, nagkaroon po ng Committee on Good Government and Public Accountability hearings po noong November 2024. At dito po nagkaroon ng statement si Ms. Gina Acosta, ang Special Disbursing Officer ng OBP, na by the directive of VP Sara, binibigay po niya ang Cash Advance for Confidential Fund kay Colonel Raymond Dante Pilachica.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Before we go into that, Your Honor, please, Presiding Officer, this witness alluded or... has testified that there was a committee on good government and public accountability CGPA hearing. Kailan to? November 2024 po. For the understanding and appreciation of this honorable court, this was subject of a motion for judicial notice of the prosecution and the transcripts of that hearing as to its Actual occurrence as to what transpired, Your Honor, have been subject of judicial notice. Your Honor, Mr. Witness, Madam Witness, sinabi mo na nag-testify si Ms. Gina Acosta.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Nandun ka ba sa hearing na iyon?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po, nandun po ako sa hearing na iyon.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Bakit ka nandun sa hearing na iyon?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Kasama po ako sa resource persons from COA na umatend po doon.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Nasubpoena ka ba?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Bakit ka sinopina?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Kasi ako po yung staff na nag-conduct ng evaluation po ng mga documents na sinubmit in relation sa likwidasyon ng confidential fund ng OBP at DepEd.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay, and you said that in that hearing of the Committee on Good Government and Public Accountability, Nag-testify ang isang Ms. Gina Acosta. Ito bang Ms. Gina Acosta yung sinabi mo kanina na Chief of Staff? Ay, hindi. Sino ba? SDO ng Office of the Vice President? Yes po, si Ms. Gina Acosta po. At nakilala mo siya sa hearing na yon? Na nandun talaga siya? Opo, nagpakilala po siya. Nagpakilala siya sa'yo?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Hindi po, doon sa hearing po, kaya na-identify ko po na
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: siya po yun. And anong sinabi niya? Anong narinig mong sinabi niya sa hearing na yan?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Na by the directive po of BP Sara, binibigay niya kay Colonel Raymond Dante Pilachica, head ng Vice Presidential Security and Protection Group, yung Cash Advance for Confidential Fund.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Na sinabi kay Gina Acosta, ng Vice President, na ibigay niya kay isang Colonel La Chica. Sino itong
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Colonel La Chica? Siya po yung head ng vice-presidential and security group po noong time na yun.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Itong Colonel La Chica, hindi siya senior disbursement officer? Special disbursement officer?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Hindi po siya ang SDO.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ano ang kinalaman ng isang head ng security sa disbursement ng Confidential Funds, kung alam mo.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Under po kasi sa Joint Circular, nakalagay po doon na sa responsibility ng SDO na siya yung mag-de-disburse ng cash advance. And meron din pong provision under 6.1.1 na under no circumstance shall cash advance for confidential fund be transferred from one accountable to another po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So, Kung ano ang nakalagay sa circular na yan, 6.1.1, yun lang dapat ang officer na dapat mag-disburse ng pondo.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po, CSDO lang po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: E paano kung ang vice president mismo, vice president, yung head ng agency, ang siya mismo nag-instruct kay Ma'am Gina Acosta, na bagay ni Gina Acosta,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Kanyang SDO, kay Colonel La Chica. Tama ba yun sa palagay n'yo o sa evaluation n'yo, Madam Witness?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly turn on the mic of the counsel for respondent, Tech, and why is it off?
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: Hello. The witness is incompetent to answer that question.
Presiding officer: If
Presiding officer: she knows, counsel, witness may answer.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: If
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: you know, Celine, if you don't, you can also say so.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Okay po, thank you po, Your Honor. Under po kasi sa Joint Circular, it is the SDO na magdidisperse ng cash advance. And ang participation po dito ng head of agency is to oversee, kasama po sa responsibility niya, to oversee the agency-wide use ng kung paano po ginagamit ang confidential fund.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So ang sagot sa tanong ay, Ang tanong ko ngayon, sa sinabi mo, sa palagay mo, bakit ka nabahala na si Ms. Acosta, I have not yet
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: asked
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: a question.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Let the counsel finish her question. Counsel, for response. Why
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: does it concern you, as you stated, that Ms. Acosta admitted to transferring the confidential funds to Colonel La Chica?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Are you done, Attorney Caponan?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, counsel, respondent. Your Honor,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the witness did not say that she was concerned about it. So that's the leading question.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Misleading,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: sorry.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly reform, counsel.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You already established that the witness heard Gina Acosta under oath testify that she was instructed by the Vice President to give the funds. What
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: observation or significance did you draw from the admission by Ms. Acosta in this Committee on Good Government and Public Accountability hearing? What observation or significance did you draw personally from this admission?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: This is a direct violation po ng Joint Circular, specifically yung item 6.1.1 po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Again, 6.1.1.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Are
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: you familiar? Are you competent to testify on what 6.1.1 is?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po. Bakit? Kasi po, ang nakalagay dito is hindi po pwedeng ibigay ito ng SD o sa ibang officer po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel for respondent.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The question is unresponsive, Your Honor. She was asked, why are you competent to testify on 6.1.1? The answer, rather, is unresponsive.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Witness is directed to answer yes or no. If she is competent, she's going ahead of the horse.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po, kasi ang basis po ng audit namin is the joint circular.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Okay. What next
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: did you do in relation? to the liquidation of the OVP's confidential funds after this committee hearing.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: After po the committee hearing together, after din po na ma-evaluate yung mga liquidation documents and yung mga responses, I drafted po a notice of disallowance and sinabit ko po ito sa aking division chief for her review.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So ikaw mismo ang nag-draft ng notice of disallowance?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Anong basis nito? Itong notice of disallowance?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ang una po is yung direct, yung kanina pong nabanggit ko na yung directive ni BP Sara na ibigay ni Ms. Gina Acosta yung cash advance for CF kay Colonel La Chica, which is a violation of under 6.1.1 of the Joint Circular. And after the evaluation po nung responses, The amount of 261,300,000 was also disallowed kasi nga po yung payment of rewards amounting to 62 million were not supported with documents evidencing success. And yung purchases po nila ng supplies and provision of medical and food aid in a total amount of 199 million based on the acknowledgement receipts po, hindi ma-ascertain na these are for purchase of supplies, kaya po nanghingi ako ng additional documents po. And yung pang-apat po is, based sa evaluation ng mga acknowledgement receipts for the third quarter, may disbursement po doon for purchase of information na nabayaran before marilis yung cash advance na nagkakahalaga ng 300,000 pesos.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay, so you is dahil dito sa mga... reasons na yan, nag-issue ka ng notice of disallowance. If shown to you, itong notice, will you be able to identify the same?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, please, can we ask Attorney de la Cruz to show us?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: This
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: has been pre-marked as Exhibit P-1-13-F, Your Honor, for the prosecution.
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: And for the record,
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: Respondents 1-9.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Please proceed, counsel.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yes, Your Honor. Again, for the record, this is likewise. Respondents exhibit the same as prosecution, which, again, they refuse to stipulate on. How much, Madam Witness, was disallowed in your notice of disallowance?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yung buong amount po na P375 million pesos.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: P375 million. Anong period ang covered nitong P375 million na to?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Bale, ito po ay for the three-quarters of 2023. Tig-125 po per quarter.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And this is being flashed on the screen as well. Sino-sino ang responsible persons in connection sa notice of disallowance na in-issue ng COA-ICFAO dated March 31, 2026.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ang mga persons po ay sina VP Sara, DSDO Ms. Gina Acosta, ang Chief Accountant Ms. Solieta Villa del Rey, at si Col. Raymond Dante Pilachica po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Now you said that respondent, Duterte, Sara Duterte, is accountable. Why? Bakit accountable ang Vice President Sara Duterte?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Because she approved po the transactions and the utilization of the cash advance po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Saan yan, saan nakalagay sa mga dokumento ang in-approve ng Vice President mismo? Yung sa accomplishment report po. sa mga lahat ng accomplishment reports. Ito naman, Ms. Gina Acosta. Why do you say that she is also accountable?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Kasi po siya ang special disbursing officer at responsibility po niya na i-disburs ang cash advance.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Pag sinabing accountable, hindi naman tayo accountant, ano sa layman's term ang ibig sabihin ng accountable?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: May yung taong may pananagutan po dun sa pondo na binigay sa kanya. May pananagutan.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So ang Sara Duterte, Vice President, may pananagutan? Opo, tama po. Bakit? Anong nature ba ng pondo na yan?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Kasi po, ito is pondo ng bayan po. Pondo ng bayan.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: In English naman, eh, public funds. Opo. Ms. Gina Acosta, bakit naman siya accountable?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Dahil siya po ang designated na special disbursing officer and responsibility po niya na i-disburs ang cash advance.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. At bakit? Hindi ba niya ginawa yung kanyang responsibility ng mag-disburs?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Objection, Your Honor. Leading question.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Why do you say that she is an accountable officer? Reform counsel.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: What?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: No, you already did. I
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: reformed, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: I know, I know, you already did. Please continue.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Pwede pong paulit yung tanong?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: You mentioned that Gina Costa ay accountable officer rin. Bakit?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Dahil sa kanya po, ibinigay yung cash advance for, siya po ang dinisigdate na special disbursing officer at siya po yung accountable dun sa pag-disburs ng cash advance for confidential fund.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sinabi mo, naging basihan mo ang joint circular.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Saan naman nakalagay ito sa joint circular na isang SDO ang dapat responsible sa pag-disburs? ng tinatawag na public funds.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Nakalagay po ito dun sa responsibility niya and gaya nung nagbanggit ko po kanina dun sa item 6.1.1 na hindi ito pwedeng i-transfer from one accountable to another. Incidentally,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: pag ganyan sa mga companies yung mga naghahandle ng mga pondo, eh may bond. May bond tinatawag, no? Dito ba? Sa office of the Vice President? Accountable?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: public disbursement officer. Saan kaya? Meron ba sa circular ang nakalagay na kailangan magbigay ng bond ang SDO? Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Leading question.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: I'll consider it preliminary, counsel, because I think it's a given that SDO should have a bond. Kindly answer, Madam Witness.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Nakalagay po ito sa joint circular. Your Honor, pwede po bang mag-refer ako sa Joint Circular?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Nakalagay po ito dun sa item 6.1.2. Sabi po dito, cash advances for CFN or IF shall be drawn by duly designated and banded SDOs or head of agency for the implementation of a program, activity, and project.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: May I
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: proceed?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So sa
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: binasa mo, ang SDO ay dapat magbigay ng bond.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Do you have any knowledge if this Gina Acosta gave a bond pursuant to the joint circular provision that you led?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po, naka-attach po ito dun sa liquidation documents. Required po ito sa joint circular.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At magkano naman kung ang amount ng Office of the Vice President Confidential Funds ay 500 million pesos? Magkano naman ang bond na sinabi mo naka-attach ang dokumento sa mga sinubmit ng OVP? Magkano ang bond?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Hindi ko na po maaalala yung kung magkano, pero based po sa evaluation ng mga documents, enough naman po yung band ng SDO para i-cover yung cash advances niya.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: If the amount is stated, is the amount stated, if you recall?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Hindi ko na po maaalala yung kung magkano yung band, pero during the evaluation po, hindi po namin naging findings yun. Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ngayon naman, if
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: the SDO, is a bonded at sinabi mo si Gina Acosta ay may bond. In the provision that you read, is it allowed for a Gina Acosta, isang bonded na senior special disbursement officer na mag-transfer ng kanyang responsibility sa isa pang officer? Your Honor, please.
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: Yes, counsel. Leading
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: question, Your Honor.
Presiding officer: Actually, I would have sustained it because she asked and answered. Already answered, counsel.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: You said, I will reform, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, she already answered that question earlier. Can I reform, counsel?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ito namang Ms. Villa del Rey. Why did you say she is an accountable officer?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Dahil po, dun sa liquidation report, sinertify niya na complete and proper yung mga liquidation documents po. Pero, upon the evaluation po, hindi po ito complete and proper.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And Colonel Achica?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Dahil po, siya ang nag-disburse ng cash advance despite not being the special disbursing officer ng Office of the Vice President.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And why is that? Is this among your observations? Yes, po. And what did your observation indicate about Colonel La Chica?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yun nga po. Ito po yung isang mga ground kung bakit po na-disallow yung total ng 375 million.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sa pagkaalam namin, based on our understanding, may mga stages yan. Ang unang stage ng evaluation ay audit.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: observation memorandum. Tama?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo, tama po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And in the case of the Office of the Vice President, naka-issue kayo ng AOM.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ang next stage dapat dyan ay ang notice of suspension. Tama?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Now, in the case of the Office of the Vice President,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Pagkatapos nagbigay ng response ang Office of the Vice President sa AOM na in-issue n'yo, anong nangyari?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Anong ginawa ng Office of the Vice President?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Nag-respond po sila sa AOM po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So nag-respond sa AOM. Did the response address? Sinagot ba? ng response na yan ang lahat ng observations, lahat ng non-compliance, lahat ng discrepancy, deficiency na pinoint out n'yo sa AOM.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Based po sa evaluation ng mga responses together with the attached documents po, hindi pa rin po ito naging compliance sa Joint Circular.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: what did you do? What did your office do, if any?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Kaya po, nag-issue po kami ng notice of disallowance.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Bakit, Madam Witness? Sa pagkaalam natin, pagkatapos ng AOM, dapat notice of suspension. Bakit n'yo agad in-issue ang isang notice of disallowance at hindi na kayo nagbigay ng notice of suspension muna? Bakit diniretso n'yo sa disallowance?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Dahil nga po sa naging statement under oath ni Ms. Gina Acosta na ibinigay niya yung, na by the directive of BP Sara, binigay niya kay Col. La Chica yung cash advance for CF, which is a violation po ng Joint Circular, making it irregular po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Apart from this Joint Circular of 2015, meron, please confirm kung meron mga rules and regulations na in-issue ang COA para sa mga settlement of accounts, if you know.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ang basis po namin is yung rules and regulations on settlement of accounts po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Anong ibig sabihin nun? Anong particular provision?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Pwede pong pakiulit yung tanong?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sinabi mo na merong rules and regulations on settlement of accounts.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo, meron po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At instead of a notice of suspension, biniretso nyo agad sa notice of disallowance.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo, tama po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Anong pinagpasihan ninyo nito?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Dahil nga po, ang definition po ng notice of disallowance based on the joint circular is yung transaction po appears to be illegal, improper, or irregular. And in this case po, yung naging transfer po is a direct violation making the transaction irregular. Kaya naging notice of disallowance na po yung in-issue namin.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So itong pag-transfer ng responsibilidad sa disbursement na hindi naman special disbursement officer. Eh sinabi mo, illegal.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Doon po siya sa irregular, which is violation po siya sa joint circular.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. So yung joint circular nakalagay illegal, improper, at irregular. Ang sinasabi mo ay irregular.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo, tama po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At bakit irregular ulit?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Kasi po
Cylene May L. Del Campo: hindi siya sum-
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: and
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: answered, Your Honor. Ask and answered already.
Presiding officer: Ask
Presiding officer: and
Presiding officer: answered, counsel. Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: What is the status of this notice of this allowance at present, if you know?
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: Ask and
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: answered
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: already.
Presiding officer: I
Presiding officer: don't quite remember, counsel. It would be okay to repeat. It
Presiding officer: was not asked
Presiding officer: yet, Your Honor. It would be okay to repeat nevertheless. Yes, Ms. Aileen.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: What is the status of this notice of this allowance?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Nasa prescribed period pa po ang OBB para po mag-appeal sa commission proper po.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: With the indulgence of counsel, and what is the prescribed period to appeal before the commission?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: 180 days po after nila ma-receive yung notice of disallowment.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Six months?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Apo.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You may proceed, counsel.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: to your knowledge, are they still well within this six-month period?
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: Ask and answered already, Your Honor.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, please, it is within, this is follow-up to the question of the presiding officer.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: What is the period? 180 days.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: My question is, is the 180 days still currently applicable?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Next, next, Madam Witness, are you still okay? Apo. Punta naman tayo dito sa Department of Education.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Before you move on, counsel, with the indulgence of Atty. Kapunan, Ma'am Cylene, so dahil binigay Diomano Calachica ni Gina Acosta, dinisallow niyo na lahat?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po kasi direct violation po ito ng Joint Circular.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Subalit dahil hindi yan dumaan sa Notice of Suspension, in-issue niyo yung Notice of Disallowance nang hindi binibigyan ng pagkakataon. Sumagot muna o magpaliwanag. ang OVP.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Wala pa po sila nun. Ngayon pa lang kung sakasakali kung mag-a-appeal sila. Opo.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So you have not heard the side of the Vice President or the OVP's office with respect to what you heard Gina Acosta say under oath in the House hearings? Wala pa silang response dun?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Wala pa po.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Dun na lang
Cylene May L. Del Campo: po sa appeal.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Dun na lamang. So ini-issue nyo ito nang hindi naririnig yung panig nila?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You may proceed, Counsel, to the DepEd.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: What is your participation, Madam Witness, in the post-audit of the confidential funds of the Office of the Vice President of Department of Education for the first quarter and second quarter of 2023, covering the periods February 20 to March 30, 2023? for the first quarter and for the second quarter, April 25 to June 30, 2023. Anong participation mo, if any, sa post-audit na to?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ako po yung nag-evaluate ng response ng DepEd sa audit observation memorandum na na-issue sa kanila for the first and second quarters of 2023 po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: You also said that earlier, that noong na-transfer na si Mr. Wamil na sinundan mo, nag-issue siya bago siya umalis ng isang AOM, dated February 1, 2024. You confirm that?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo, tama po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And to your knowledge, to your knowledge, nagbigay ba ng sagot or response? ang DepEd, Department of Education, na ang head of agency ay si Vice President Sara Duterte. Meron bang response ang office ng DepEd sa AOM dated February 1, 2024 na in-issue ni Mr. Wamil?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo, nag-submit po sila ng response noong April 17, 2024.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And if I show you a copy of this response dated April 17, 2024, ma-identify mo ba siya?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Showing to you now, Attorney de la Cruz. Showing to you now, the Department of Education's response, pre-marked as Exhibit P-1-21-B.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: P-1-21-B, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly turn on, thank you, and respondents, 1-9, counsel, correct?
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: Yes, Your Honor,
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: it's 1-79. Ah,
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: 79. DE. Ah, sorry, 1- The response is 1- D
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: -1-79, DE.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Madam Witness,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: anong relation itong document na in-identify mo sa sinabi mong sinubmit na response? ng DepEd Secretary.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: This
Cylene May L. Del Campo: is the
Cylene May L. Del Campo: same response po na sinubmit sa amin ng DepEd.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Please look at this document. Meron nakalagay sa last page. Kaninong signature ito kung alam mo?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Kay Atty. Michael Wesley T. Powa po. Atty.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Michael... Who is this Atty. Michael Powa?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Based on this document po, Undersecretary and Chief of Staff.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Why are you familiar with his signature?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Doon po sa dalawang documents na na-evaluate ko, pareho po yung signature niya doon sa dalawang transmittal letters po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And how many acknowledgment?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: What were the attachments, if you recall, to this response of the DepEd?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Nag-submit po sila ng acknowledgement receipts, certification from the relevant partners, specifically the Armed Forces of the Philippines.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ano pa?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: At saka po, fully accomplished na disbursement voucher. And meron din po pala silang sinubmit na DepEd Order No. 1.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: You mentioned na may unattached response na acknowledgement receipts for the first quarter and for the second quarter.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes,
Cylene May L. Del Campo: po.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo, tama po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Meron kang summary na ginawa. Opo, meron po. Dala mo ba yung summary na yan?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yes po. Your Honor, please, the witness is producing a summary of 561 acknowledgement receipts for the first quarter liquidation expenses of confidential funds of the Department of Education.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Observation of counsel is noted. We
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: are giving copies to Respondent's Council. and to this honorable presiding officer through the clerk of court.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The clerk of court to those eyes directed to kindly get the copy.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: may proceed, counsel.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: We request, Your Honor, that this...
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: For the first quarter prepared by the witness, we mark as exhibit P-1-33.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Madam Witness, for
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: the second quarter of the DepEd, attached to the DepEd's response is 619. acknowledgement receipts. Do you confirm that?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: This is for the period April 25 to June 30, 2023.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And this consists... No. Do you have that summary with you?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, po. Meron po.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Same order. Kindly mark it and furnish the composing counsel as well as the accord to the copy.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: For the record, Your Honor, the first quarter... is 561 acknowledgement receipts. The second quarter is 619 acknowledgement receipts. So the summaries of quarter one and quarter two consist of 1,180 acknowledgement receipts, Your Honor.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: These are marked. We request that this be marked as Exhibit PI-34 for the second quarter. Madam Witness, anong proseso ang ginamit mo sa paggawa ng evaluation or tabulation na to?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Gaya po nang ginawa ko rin sa OBP, tinabulate ko po ito by date, per yung activity and the amount po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: familiar ka sa mga ARs na to, Madam Witness?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And if shown to you, we will show you some selected examples.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: also going to be flashed on the screen.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Showing to you,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Exhibit P-1-17-29 being flashed on the screen.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Madam Witness, anong
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: pangalan na nakalagay dito?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Perma lang po. Ay, hindi ko po mabasa kung perma ito, pero wala pong... Walang pangalan, pero may perma. Opo.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And anong place na in-issue?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Based po sa dokumento, ang address po is Danao.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At ang date?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: February 21, 2023 po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: February 21, 2023 for magkano?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: P50,000 pesos po for the payment for information.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Can you read the others?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: P-17, P-1-17-81, Alfred
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Avanta.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Nakalagay po. Acknowledgement receipt date, February 21, 2023. Receive the amount of 100,000 in payment for supplies. P.E. Alfred Abanta, adress Malolos. Malolos.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Next, P-1-17-288, Mary Santillan. Some place in issue ito, Madam Witness, based on
Cylene May L. Del Campo: the document. based po sa document, ang address po nakalagay is Davao City.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Anong date nito?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: February 21, 2023 po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: The same date,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: February 21, 2023. Okay. Galing Malolos, pumunta ng Davao, Negros, Oksidental naman, P-1-17-382, Ameliu.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Magkano to?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: 45,000 po in payment for rental safe house.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ang date?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: February 21, 2023 po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And place is?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ang nakalagay po sa dokumento na address is Negros Occidental.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Negros Occidental. For
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: the next one, P-1-17-492. Kaninong pangalan ito?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Pirma lang po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Walang pangalan, may pirma. Saan naman place?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Binigay ang perang ito.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: San Francisco, Agusan del Sur, po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So, from Negros Occidental, pumunta ng Agusan. Your Honor,
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: please,
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: Your Honor. Magkano ang, there's
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: no
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: question yet.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Ano ang
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: date?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: I know where you're getting at, but kindly finish your question, counsel.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Anong date ang inisyo nito, based on this
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: document?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Date po is February 21, 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay, the next document.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel for respondent, yes.
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: Your Honor, can the counsel be reminded not to make any inferences on the document, Your Honor, like from
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: lolos,
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: pumunta ng negros.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel is so reminded, just ask your question to the witness. Let the witness be the one to respond to whatever elicitation or admission you want to get, Counsel.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yes, Your Honor, we will comply, although it's self-evident that all these documents are dated February 21, 2023, like the next one, P-1-17493, in the name of Andrie Galor. Where was it issued, Madam Witness?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Based po sa document, ang address po is Makati City.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And what date?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: February 21, 2023 po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: For what amount, Madam Witness?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: 100,000 po for the payment of rental safe house.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: the last in this first set is P-1-17-574. Is there a name? Anong pangalan na nakalagay sa dokumento?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Minda Lacson
Cylene May L. Del Campo: po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Anong date?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: February 21, 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Anong place?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Negros Oriental po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Madam Witness, based on the documents, one, two, three, four,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: five, six, based
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: on the seven selected documents presented to you, do you confirm that there is only one date of disbursement? Your Honor, please.
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: I'm asked and answered.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: 21, 2023 is the uniform dates. In all of these documents, Madam Witness, I have not yet asked the question. You already
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: did, counsel, if it's the uniform date.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: The question is this. What significance can you draw or observation can you make for these six documents issued on the same dates in six different places from seven? Danao, Malolos, Davao, Negros, Agusan, Makati, Sito, Negros, Oriental. What observation can you make, if any, as regards these acknowledgement receipts that you identified?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Based po dito sa mga acknowledgement receipts na to, lahat po sila is dated February 21, 2023.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: na ibigay po sila sa iba-ibang addresses po na nakalagay dito.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: You mentioned earlier on testimony that you have audited many national agencies, correct?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And at least 30, if I recall right.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: least 30 national agencies? Opo. Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Based on your evaluation, how
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: many government or national agencies have had similar submissions on acknowledgement receipts. If you recall, same date, different locations, different names. How many, based on your recollection, national or local government agencies have submitted acknowledgement receipts of this nature?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Hindi ko na po mabilang pero may mga nagsasabit din po ng acknowledgement receipts po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ang tanong sa'yo, acknowledgement receipts na pare-parehong araw pero iba-ibang location. Meron ka bang maalala?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Parang wala. Wala
Cylene May L. Del Campo: naman po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Please go over this.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Again, acknowledgement receipts by way of liquidation. for the DepEd.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Can you please go over this one
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: by one, being flashed on the screen. First is P-1-17-7 for Geraldine Omoy.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: What date is stated there?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Nakalagay po dito, February 25, 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And place?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Nakalagay po sa dokumento na to, ang address po is Masbate.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Magkano?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: 200,000 po for the payment of reward.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Next, P-1-17-87. Kaninong pangalan na nandyan?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Perma lang po yung nakalagay. Walang pangalan.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Saan in-issue?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Sa Lawag City po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Anong date?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: February 25, 2023 po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: February 25,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: 2023 for how much?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: 100,000 po for the payment for supplies.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: P-1-17-88 to Mr. Aquino, Jaime Aquino, from Davao City, magkano? 45
Cylene May L. Del Campo: ,000 po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And what date?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: February 25, 2023 po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Next,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: P-1-17-127, whose name is it, what amount, and
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: what date?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Perma lang po, tapos ang date po niya is February 25, 2023. Ang nakalagay po na address is Agusan del Norte.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Next, Madam Witness. Rex Napoles, P-1-17-128. What date, what place, and what amount is stated?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ang date po is February 25, 2023.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: 50,000 in payment for transport, rental, or expenses. Ang address po na nakalagay is Olonga po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: P-1-17-169, Madam Witness, whose
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: name,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: what is the date, the place, and the amount?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ang date po is February 25, 2023. In the amount of 40,000 for the payment of information, address po is Samar.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: p-1-17-213, Eduardo Tan. What date and where was it disbursed? And what amount?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Nakalagay po sa dokumento, date, February 25, 2023. Ang amount po is 150,000 in payment for reward. Ang address po is Masbate. With
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the intelligence of counsel, so as not to belabor the point. Based on your understanding, Ma'am Cylene, yung address po bang nakalagay sa baba? Address kung saan binigay yung pera o address nung tao? Sa pagkakaunawan nyo po ah.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Based po dito sa, dahil po documents evidencing payment, yung address po dito is yung kung saan po binayad.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So ang ibig sabihin, pro forma document po ba yan?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Hindi po ito kasama sa annexes sa joint circular. So
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: hindi ito pro forma?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Hindi po.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So pag sa pagkakaunawa nyo lamang po na ang address na nakalagay dyan, address kung saan binigay. Hindi address kung taga saan sila.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo kasi based po sa ito po ay documents evidencing payment so yung address dito is kung saan po binayaran.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: And that is reflected in the AUM you issued with respect to the first and second quarter?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Hindi po.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Wala sa AUM yan?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Wala po. Okay.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, you may proceed.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Mr. Lito Saludoyanez, P-117-237, what date was it issued or paid? San binayad ang pera? Anong date
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: at anong amount?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ang date po is February 25, 2023. Payment for supplies amounted to 50,000. Ang address po is Lubok.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Pangasinan naman, P-1-17-238, isang Janine Bartolin. What date was this disbursed?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ang nakalagay po rito is February 25, 2023, in the amount of 50,000 for payment for supplies po, ang address Pangasinan. P
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: -1-17-238, Janine Bartolina.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ito, I'm sorry, 369. P-1-17-369. Whose name is this?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Signature lang po. Walang pangalan. Saan in-issue? Saan binayad itong perang ito? Compostela Valley po. P-1-17-391.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Lulito Agord. Please state the date it was paid, the place, and
Cylene May L. Del Campo: the amount. February 25, 2023 po, payment for rental of safe house amounting to 45,000. Ang address po na nakalagay is Davao City. Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: There are one, two, three, four, five,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: six.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: There are seven remaining acknowledgement receipts here. I'll go over them briefly. Please follow as I mentioned them. P-1-17-418, only a signature appears.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Disbursed in Masbate for 50,000. Again, February 25, 2023. P-1-17.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: 430, in the name of Andre, La Serna. La Serna. Issued, disbursed in Nueva Ecija for 100,000, again dated February 25, 2023. Can you go over it? P-1-17-431, in the name of Hamil Haldon, disbursed in Coronadal City for 100,000. Also dated February 25, 2023, an acknowledgement receipt P-1-17-479, no name, signature only, disbursed in Batangas for the amount of 9,000. Again, dated February 25, 2023, John V. Manta, received in Kalinga, Apayaw, 50,000 pesos. On February 25, 2023, Exhibit P-117-480, P-117-481, Rona de Vera received 50,000 pesos in South Leyte. Also, on February 25, 2023, and lastly, a signature received. In ABRA, 50,000 pesos, P-1-17-540, also on February 25,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: 2023, based on these acknowledgement receipts. Do you confirm?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Madam Witness?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Apo. That what was stated is accurate, based on the records. Based po
Cylene May L. Del Campo: sa mga acknowledgement receipts po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: What
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: observation can you make or significance do you draw from these documents
Cylene May L. Del Campo: presented to you? Based po dun sa documents na parinissent sa akin, lahat po ito is dated Feb 25, 2023 po, with different addresses po na nakalagay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: on the same date, disbursements on the same date, with different addresses. What observation, if any, can you draw from this?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yun nga po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: With different addresses?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Apo.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Locations? Is this, again, kuklarify, is this a place where the money was disbursed or where the money was received?
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: Your Honor, please. Witnesses incompetent, Your Honor. to testify on that matter. Your
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: Honor, she is
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: confident. Based on the document, again, that was the earlier question of the presiding officer, address ba to nung binigyan o address to kung saan binigay?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Based po sa document as documents evidencing payment kung saan po binigay yung address.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Ang
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: ibig
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: sabihin, ang
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: ibig sabihin kung saan binigay, ang ibig bang sabihin, correct me if I'm wrong, Madam Witness, on the same date. Itong mga binigyan ng confidential funds ay nasa different locations ba, Madam Witness?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Based po sa documents, opo.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And based sa joint circular na sinabi mo, sino dapat ang mag-distribute or mag-disburse ng pera, perang nakalagay dito?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: It is the responsibility po ng special disbursing officer.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So, tama bang sabihin, correct me if I'm wrong, kung mali naman ang understanding ko, tama bang sabihin na ang special disbursement officer, eh sa isang araw, eh pinuntahan lahat itong lokasyon na ito? Tama ba ang interpretation ko? Your Honor, please. If she knows, Your Honor, she was the one who evaluated these documents.
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: Your Honor, that calls for a conclusion of fact.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Witness is not competent to answer the question, counsel. I think let the document speak for itself. That if indeed the SDO is the only officer authorized to disburse the funds, then clearly it is physically impossible to be in all of these locations in one day. And there was earlier admission that the SDO gave the funds to a Colonel Lachica, probably even more. So that remains to be seen and proven in the coming days. Please proceed, counsel.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Who is the special disbursement officer of the DepEd? Sa
Cylene May L. Del Campo: DepEd po is si Mr. Edward Fajarda.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And based on your definition of a special disbursement officer, si Mr. Fajarda ang authorized na magbigay ng lahat na ito, Madam Witness?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Going now.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: With the indulgence of counsel, so sa ilalim ng joint circular, siya lang walang iba?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po, ito po ay nakasama sa kanyang responsibility. At based on item 6.1.1 po, hindi po ito pwedeng i-transfer from one accountable to another.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So, based on these documents, kasi sinabi mo, si Mr. Fajarda, so makikita naman natin as observed by the presiding officer, these were many locations in one day. Ngayon,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Mr. Fajarda, Special Disbursement Officer, alam mo ba kung may sinubmit na dokumento si Mr. Fajarda na nag-iindicate sa COA o COA ICFAO na inauthorize niya kung sino mang ibang individual na mag-distribute nitong kapirahan na to sa mga iba-ibang taong ito sa ibang places na to, meron bang inattached na letter or acknowledgement si Mr. Fajarda o hindi Mr. Fajarda, yung head of agency, si vice president or deputy secretary
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sara Duterte, meron bang siyang sinubmit na authorization na binigay kay Mr. Fajarda na siyang disbursement officer para i-delegate sa iba ni Mr. Fajarda yung pagpunta sa iba-ibang lugar na to sa isang araw lang? Meron bang dokumentong ganun na authorization ang tinanggap ng office mo?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ang natanggap po namin na authorization or designation is si B.P. Sara ang nag-designate kay Mr. Edward Fajarda as Special Disbursing Officer ng Department of Education. Naka-attach po ito dun sa liquidation documents.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So may certification si Vice President kay Mr. Fajarda. Aside from Mr. Fajarda, meron bang ibang pangalan na nakalagay dyan sa dokumento?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Wala po. Ang nakalagay lang po doon is si Mr. Fajardo ang designated na special disbursing officer ng DepEd po for confidential fund.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Punta naman tayo, last batch na to.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Meron naman tayong another list, no?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Attached to the response of the Office of the Vice President. Para sa acknowledgement receipts dated March 15.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: 2023. Liquidation ng Vice President, I'm sorry, ng DepEd. Again, please go over this acknowledgement receipts.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: This is for what quarter, Atty. Kapunan?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: This is for the third, this is for the same quarter, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: First and second.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: First and second quarter, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Of 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yes, Your Honor. And we're talking about, again, From a list of 1049 acknowledgement receipts, we have selected a few.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Madam Witness, showing to you several selected ones. I'm showing to you, being flashed on the screen. P-1-17-57, and I will go over this list very briefly if you can follow me. Adolfo Molina, Date, March 15, 2023, Buda, Marilog, Davao City, for 50,000 pesos. P-1-17-58, walang pangalan, signature only. Date, March 15, 2023, Tandag, 30,000 pesos. P-1-17-107, wala na namang pangalan, signature only. Binayad sa Puerto Galera, Mindoro, 65,000 pesos. Date, the same, March 15, 2023. Jeline Espino, Laguna, 50,000 pesos. Date, March 15, 2023. Walang pangalan, P-1-17. Signature only. Date, March 15, 2023, sa Agusan del Norte, 40,000 pesos. Kay Rex Napoles, tumanggap ng 50,000 pesos sa Olongapo. On the same date, March 15, 2023, P-1-17-128. Next, Piano Recto, P-1-17-148, sa Zamboanga City. 40,000 pesos. Mr. Julio Izguera, Tagabutuan City, tumanggap ng 100,000 pesos, P-1-17-189, also on March 15, 2023. Are you following, Madam Witness? Yes. P-1-17, walang pangalan, signature only, Davao City. 925,000 pesos. Another 50,000 pesos sa walang pangalan, signature only, P-1-17-226, na-issued or disbursed in Nabunturan. From Nabunturan, Laguna, 50,000 pesos sa isang Nizel T, P-1-17-227. Isang walang signature, tumanggap sa Dasmariñas, Cavite ng 65,000 pesos, P-1-17-259 on March 15, 2023. Carmen Sevillano, taga Surigao del Norte, tumanggap ng 50,000 on the same date, March 15, 2023, P-1-17-260. Tama? Apo. Okay. Can you continue?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Dito po sa P
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: -1-17-311. P-17-261, walang pangalan, tama? Signature only. Saan naman ito in-issue?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Quezon City po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ito naman, P-117-311, walang pangalan, signature, Bacoor, P50,000. Si Alice Cresencio, tumanggap, galing Iligan City, P25,000. On the same date, March 15, 2023, P-117-349. P-117406, walang pangalan, signature lang. Galing naman tarlak, 50,000 pesos on the same day, March 15, 2023. Walang pangalan, signature lang, galing Pasay City, tumanggap ng 65,000 pesos. P-71-17-422, isang signature na tumanggap. galing Kalbayog, Samar, 45,000 pesos, walang pangalan, March 15, 2023, P-117-423, P-117-447, again, no name, Campos, Telag, Valley, tumanggap ng 100,000 pesos, on the same day, March 15, 2023, another signature received, hindi mabasa ito, San Juan City, unreadable, 30,000 pesos, on the same day, March 15, 2023, P-117, 468. Another signature received, walang pangalan, sa Aguinaldo Ifugao, tumanggap ng 100,000 pesos, on March 15, 2023, P-117. Your Honor, please. Three more... Three more, Your Honor. Four more.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: We get the point, counsel. We get the point. And it's in the tabulation anyway of the witness.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Now, Madam Witness, sa mga binasa natin at sa mga na-observe mo, anong significance nitong acknowledgement receipts na pinakita
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: sa'yo?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ito po ang proof of payments po nung confidential fund. And based po dito, all dated March 15, 2023 with different addresses po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: All dated? March 15, 2023. So sino
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: dapat, based on your circular, ang nag
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: -disburse nitong mga pondong to?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ang dapat pong mag-disburse ay ang special disbursing officer.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At sino nga ang special disbursing officer na yan?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ito po ay sa DepEd po si Mr. Edward Fajarda.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Kung hindi naman, kasi nung binabasa ko ito, kasi ako, Marvel Comics ang binabasa ko, Superman ang favorite ko. Kung hindi man Superman ang isang SDO, kaya ba niyang puntahan? Sa palagay mo? Lahat na ito.
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, counsel, respondent. The question
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: is speculative, Your Honor.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: What
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: is speculative about Superman? He can fly anywhere one day.
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: It's
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: a
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: hypothetical question.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, move on. Move on, Counsel. We get your point.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Madam Witness, what other documents? Although, can we ask that Superman remain on record? We
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: did not strike it off, Counsel. The Presiding Officer simply asked you to move on.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Madam Witness, what other documents, if any? Ano pang mga dokumento? Apart from this
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: acknowledgement receipts for the first and second quarter constituting 1,049 documents. 1,049 documents for the first quarter and second quarter.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: I'm sorry.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: 561
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: and 619, Your Honor, or 1,180 for the debit. Anong other documents ang inattach ng DepEd?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: To support po the payment of rewards, nag-attach po sila ng certifications from relevant partners, specifically the Armed Forces of the Philippines po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And itong mga certifications ng Armed Forces, if shown to you, would you be able to identify them?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Showing to you.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Showing to you a certification dated January 1, 2024, issued by Colonel Manalos M. Buran Singh, marked as Exhibit P-1-22-A, stipulated upon by the Defense Council, Your Honor, respondent. Certification dated December 30, 2023, issued by Colonel Carlos B. Sangandaan, Jr., previously marked Exhibit B-122B, likewise stipulated upon common exhibit with defense or respondent. Certification dated December 5, 2023, issued by Colonel Magtanggol. Panopio, marked as exhibit P-1-22-C up to P-1-22-C-1. Again, stipulated by counsel for the respondent. And certification issued by Colonel Adonis R. Bajau, previously marked as exhibit P-1-22-D. Showing to you these exhibits. Madam Witness. and as well being flashed on the screen for easy reference of this honorable court. What relation do these certifications, which are both prosecution and defense exhibits, what do these certifications have in relation to this certification you said was issued by the armed forces?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: These are the same certifications po na naka-attach sa kanilang response. Anong significance naman ng certifications na to?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Dito po sa certification na to, inattach po nila ito bilang proof of success of the information gathering and or surveillance activities.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At ito bang proof of success e compliant sa circular na pinagbasihan mo?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: During my evaluation po, Opo, nag-compliant po ito
Cylene May L. Del Campo: dun
Cylene May L. Del Campo: sa Joint Circular.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: What
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: action, if any, pagkatapos na-receive itong certification, ito ba yung sinabi ni Atty. Wamil na pro forma? Hindi
Cylene May L. Del Campo: po, iba po yun.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ngayon, ano ang actions taken by your office with regards to this certification, if any?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ito po, Based po sa evaluation, ito po ay compliant po sa Joint Circular.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: anong in-issue n'yo, if any?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: For the first and second quarter po ng 2023 for the DepEd, we issued po a credit notice.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Anong ibig sabihin? What do you mean by a credit notice? A credit
Cylene May L. Del Campo: notice po is issued pag... Pagkatapos ng evaluation ng documents, yung liquidation documents po are found in order po and passed in audit na.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ngayon, itong credit notice na in-issue, ito ba ay final?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ang credit notice po, pwede pong, meron po sa Rules and Regulation of Settlement of Accounts na pwede pong ma-reopen ang settled account na gaya po nung pag nag-issue kami ng credit notice, pwede pa po itong ma-reopen.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Anong, what reason would you have? for reopening a credit notice.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Under po the, under the RRSA po, account settled can be reopened if before the expiration noong three years after the settlement is nagkaroon po ng, yung transaction is tainted with fraud collusion and new material evidence po were discovered during the three-year period po na yun.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: We now go, Madam Witness, punta naman tayo sa third quarter ng liquidation ng confidential funds ng DepEd. Anong participation mo dito?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ako po ang task na mag-evaluate sa response ng DepEd for the third quarter of 2023. And
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: what did you do, if any?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Currently po, this is still under evaluation and review pa po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sinabi mo na ikaw ang in-charge ng pag-evaluate. What did you evaluate?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Nung ma-issue po noong August 8, 2024, yung Audit Observation Memorandum, nag-submit po ang Department of Education ng response noong August 27, 2024.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Nag-mention ka. You mentioned an AOM. If shown to you, would you be able to identify the same? Yes po. Showing to you, Madam Witness, an
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: AOM.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Please go over it.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: This was, for the record, this was previously marked as exhibit P-1-21-C. It is an AOM dated August 8, 2024.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Stipulated upon by defense, counsel, or counsel for the respondent.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Is this the same? document that you received?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, po. Ito po yung same audit observation memorandum na in-issue po namin sa DepEd.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. On the third page, please go to the third page. There appears to be a signature over the name Nilda Plaras. Whose signature is this, if you know?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Si Assistant Commissioner Nilda Plaras po ang officer in charge ng ICFAO noong panahon na na-issue tong UN.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And you said earlier you're familiar with her signature.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: What were the findings in
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: this AOM?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yung AOM po na ito is na-issue because first, yung submitted liquidation documents lack documents evidencing payment. Pangalawa po, yung payment of rewards were not supported with documents evidencing success. Yung third po is hindi nakalagay sa PFP yung specific confidential activities na magiging basis ng disbursement for confidential fund. Pangapat po, yung disbursement voucher hindi nakalagay yung specific period or duration ng implementation po ng confidential activities. At yung panglima po, Meron pong pinaggamitan yung confidential fund na purchase of information relative to car loan scams whose victims are mostly personnel of the Department of Education. Madam
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Witness, this document is being flashed on the screen. Let us go to your first finding. Okay. Ano ang dahilan dahil nag-issue ka ng finding na yan? Yung first finding na sinabi mo.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Hindi po, ito po yung first finding, hindi po kasi nasubmit yung documents evidencing payment po to support the liquidation. Kaya po, nakasama siya sa AOM.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And what is the significance of this non-submission? if any.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Hindi po namin makikita kung sino-sino po yung binayaran at recipients nung confidential fund. Dito po kasi makikita yun sa documents evidencing payments.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yung
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: second finding mo na
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: naka-flash the screen, ano ang significance nitong finding mo?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Based po dun sa sinabit nila na accomplishment report, meron pong pinaggamitan ng payment of rewards amounting to 6,371,000 na wala pong attachment ng documents evidencing success.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: your third findings?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Hindi po nakalagay sa physical and financial plan yung specific confidential activities na paggagamitan ng confidential funds. Why is this significant? Para po ma-check kung paano nila gagamitin, dito po kasi sa physical and financial plan, dito nakikita kung paano nila gagamitin yung confidential fund nila. Eh dito po sa sinabit nila, hindi naka-specify kung anong confidential activities po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay, yung fourth. Yung fourth finding ninyo.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ano
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: itong
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: significance kung bakit nakalagay dyan sa AOM?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Under item 6.1.5 po ng Joint Circular, dapat nakalagay sa disbursement voucher yung duration ng implementation ng project. Pero yung naka-attach po na disbursement voucher, hindi po nakalagay yung period.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And your last finding? What is the reason? Bakit nakalagay yan sa AOM?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yun pong... accomplishment report nila, meron po silang ibinayad for purchase of information for, dun nga po, relative to car loan scams na hindi kasama dun sa sa enumeration at hindi intended to support the mandate of the operation of the Department of Education. Kaya po, nakasama po siya sa AOM.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Madam Witness, after
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: this AOM was issued and you have furnished, the DepEd, correct? Opo. Ano ang ginawa ng DepEd, if any?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Noong nareceive po nila ito, nagsubmit po sila ng response noong August 27, 2024.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, please, this response being referred to by the witness is a stipulated document. It is Exhibit P-1-21-D now being shown to the witness.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Madam Witness, is this the same?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: response.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo, ito po yung same response na sinubmit sa amin ng DepEd po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And, Madam Witness, what documents, if you recall, were attached to this response of the DepEd?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Nagsubmit po sila ng mga acknowledgement receipts as documents evidencing payments. nagsabit din po sila ng mga certification from the Armed Forces of the Philippines to support the payment of rewards po. And nagsabit din po sila
Cylene May L. Del Campo: ng
Cylene May L. Del Campo: accomplished na disbursement voucher na nakalagay po rin yung period covered by the cash advance.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: You mentioned several acknowledgement receipts and we have selected a few acknowledgement receipts. Your Honor, please.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Import of these acknowledgement receipts are the same as the first and second set. They indicate, Your Honor, and by way of manifestation, they indicate that all of these acknowledgement receipts were issued and the amounts disbursed on one date, August 9, 2023, to different people. in different locations. Does
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the witness have a tabulation and or summary?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yes, Your Honor.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, we have a tabulation and summary.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Previously marked? Not yet, counsel.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: It has not been marked, Your Honor, and we request that this, after identification by the witness, be marked as Exhibit P-I-35. Tabulation being shown. or being furnished counsel for the respondent and this honorable court.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly furnished counsel for respondent as well as the presiding officer with a copy of your tabulation. Miss Sylene, kayo po ang gumawa ng tabulation na ito?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Opo.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Tulad ng paghahanda, tabulation na ginawa ninyong nauna ninyong ginawa para sa ibang quarters ng OVP at ng DPED?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You may proceed, counsel.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, please, this tabulation.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: On its face, this tabulation will show the acknowledgement receipts. And as earlier indicated, we will dispense with going over selected acknowledgement receipts, the purpose of which principally is to show that one single disbursement officer, Mr. Fajarda, issued on August 9, 2023 to several locations from Luzon, Visayas, Mindanao on one date, Your Honor. And I can ask the witness to confirm this based on the documents.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Not all counsel, but several.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Several selected documents. I can name the markings. P-1-17-1246, P-1- All P-1-17, 1246, 1247, 1281, 1320, 1321, 1361, 1398, 1399, 1435, 1486, 1587, 1626, 1627, 1628, 1745, 1820, 1871, and 1872, all indicating several recipients, several locations, one date, and I will ask the witness, who is the disbursing officer for this third quarter?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ang SDO po ng DepEd ay si Mr. Edward Fajarda.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yes,
Cylene May L. Del Campo: po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: indicating or designating another person outside Mr. Fajarda to disperse these various amounts in various places on this date, Madam Witness. Any document attached to the submission?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Wala po. Yung designation lang po ni Mr. Fajarda. Among these, that's
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: for the record, Your Honor, among these submissions, is the name of Joel Chua.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: That's not Chua, counsel, that's Chu.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yes, Your Honor.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Upon verification by this representation, he denies any family connection, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Proceed, counsel.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: The signature, Madam Witness, will you go to this document? Yes, po. The signature is in?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Chinese character. Can we ask fellow prosecutor to identify his signature?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: That would be self-serving counsel. Move on, counsel. Move on. Madam
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: witness, outside this acknowledgement receipts, you said that there was no separate document indicating any authorized officer to disburse these amounts in different places on set date. Madam witness, you confirm that? Yes po. Outside acknowledgement receipts, what other document was submitted by way of liquidation?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: To support po the payment of rewards, they submitted certifications from the Armed Forces of the Philippines.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And if these certifications are shown to you, Madam Witness, would you be able to identify the same?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Showing to you,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Madam Witness. and being flashed on the screen with the kind indulgence of the Honorable Presiding Officer, there is a certification dated September 25, 2023, issued by J. Chris John Mendoza, Prosecution Exhibit P-1-22-E, stipulated as well by the defense. Certification dated December 10, 2023, P-1-22-F, Also issued by Jai Chris, John F. Mendoza. Exhibit P-1-22G is a certification dated December 12, 2023. Issued by an Adonis R. Bajau. Likewise, a defense exhibit, Your Honor, certification dated July 1, 2024. Issued by a certain Darren E. Comilla.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Prosecutions Exhibit P-1-22-8. All certifications, Your Honor, for are likewise defense documents.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Do you confirm, Madam Witness, that these were part of the submissions of the DEPEN?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes, po. Kasama po yan sa response nila sa AOM for the third quarter.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: What relation do these certifications have to the one you mentioned? Are they the same?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po, pareho
Cylene May L. Del Campo: pong certification.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And what observations have you made as regards this certification?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Currently po, the review and evaluation po noong compliance na ito ng Department of Education po is under review pa po at evaluation. Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: In connection with the earlier certifications which I asked you, you mentioned certain credit notice. And you said that this credit notice says which you issued is not final. Yes. Correct? Now, tell us what would be the grounds for opening a credit notice, if you know.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: ang account po na-settled can be reopened kasi po if the transaction is tainted with fraud, collusion, or new material evidence were discovered before mag-expire yung three-year period po ng settlement ng account.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So you're saying that even if because of the certifications submitted as to this activities, a credit notice was issued. In the three-year period,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: your
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: office, COA, ICFAO, can reopen on the ground of... What are these grounds again?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: If the transaction is tainted with fraud collusion
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: or... What do you mean by fraud in the transactions?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: May anomalya po sa paggamit po noong pondo.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ano pa?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: And new material evidence were discovered before the expiration of the three-year period.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: The
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: second ground. And the third ground is?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: May nadescover po na material evidence before the expiration of the three-year period.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Now, Madam Witness, what is the current status of the evaluation of the response? You said earlier, dahil sa action taken by the COA-ICFAO, nag-respond ang DepEd. What is the status of that response?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ini-evaluate pa po na.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: third quarter, September 30, July 12 to September 30, 2023, if you know.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: This is under evaluation and review pa po?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Under evaluation. Bakit hanggang ngayon ay under evaluation?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Ito po ay under evaluation pa din hanggang ngayon kasi po this transaction po composed of voluminous documents na kailangang pag-aaralan. And sa review process po namin, pagkatapos ko po itong ma-evaluate, iaakyat ko po ito sa aking division chief na extensive din po ang kanyang pagdadaan ng review. And after po sa division chief, aakyat pa po ito sa officer in charge ng ICFAO for further review po. And sa ICFAO po kasi kulang po kami sa manpower and marami po kaming nare-receive na iba-ibang documents from different agencies po na meron din ganito karaming mga documentations po. And itong mga agencies po ito, fair po ang aming pag-treat sa kanila kaya po binibigyan namin ng pansin lahat po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay, now Madam Witness. In his testimony, when asked, Attorney Mr. Wamil said that based on his evaluation, during the period that he was there with the COA-ICFAO, he made a finding that these documents submitted by the OVP and the DepEd for that particular period he was in the COA-ICFAO were irregular based on The guidelines are based on the joint circular that you cited. To you, Madam Witness, you who took over these same documents that were submitted and who made your own independent valuation, what would you say are these documents?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: What can you say about these documents submitted by the OVP and the DepEd based on your post? audit, evaluation.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yung sa OBP po, ito ay irregular po dahil hindi po ito naging compliant sa Joint Circular. During the time naman po na-evaluate ko ang Department of Education, compliant po sila sa Joint Circular. Pero gaya nga po nang nasabi, pwede po may reopen itong settled account ng Department of Education po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Merong sinayit si Atty. Wamil na prima facie evidence na you're not a lawyer but under accounting rules, tama ba yung interpretation na pag hindi kompleto, if the documents submitted based on 8.3 of the Joint Circular, if the documents completed submitted by way of liquidation of confidential funds are not complete. Ano ang epekto nito based on the circular?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Under po sa joint circular dun sa under 8.1 nga po, failure of the accountable officer to liquidate is a prima facie evidence na this is for, nagamit po ito for personal use and benefit.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: You said that prima facie, failure of the accountable officer. At earlier, tinanong ka, ang accountable officer ng OVP is the head of agency. Meaning, sino
Cylene May L. Del Campo: yun? Si Vice President Sara Duterte po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At sa DepEd naman, sino ang head of agency?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: During the time po noong 2023, it is Vice President Sara Duterte din po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And under 8.3, ang presumption is, naging use, to quote, paki-quote, use for personal...
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Sabi po sa 8.3, failure of the accountable officer to liquidate is a prima facie evidence that he or she used the missing funds for personal use and benefit.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Madam Witness, my last question to you, Madam Witness.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Let's go back to this hearing in... Committee on Good Government Accountability. And there is an admission there, Madam Witness, in your testimony here, that you, in that hearing, Gina Acosta, Chief of Staff of the VP, admitted, of the SDO, I'm sorry, admitted to transferring confidential funds, tama, to Colonel La Chica.
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: Honor, please.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: There's no
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: question yet, Your Honor. Your Honor, the exact wordings of the counsel cannot be verified without reflecting the TSNs that she is referring to.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: I'm referring to the testimony of this witness. Besides, in the previous hearing, there is judicial notice already of the TSNs.
Presiding officer: No, no, that's not it, counsel. Witness already admitted in her earlier testimony that she was there. When Gina Acosta testified before the House of Representatives and heard her testify, based on her recollection of what she said, she may answer. Kindly finish your last question, counsel.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: I forgot. You repeat my question. What did I say? Wala pa akong question. Okay. Based on this admission of Gina Acosta that indeed...
Cylene May L. Del Campo: May nabanggit din po noon si Mr. Fajarda na binibigay niya yung confidential fund kay Colonel Nolasco po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: May naging admission under oath. May admission din under oath. In the same
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: hearing, Madam Witness? Yes po. What was that admission?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Sinabi din po ni Mr. Edward Fajarda na SDO ng DepEd na binibigay po niya yung cash advance for confidential fund kay Colonel Nolasco.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And who is this Fajarda?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Siya po ang Special Disbursing Officer ng Department of Education.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: and who
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: is Nolasco.
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Isa po siya sa mga, part po siya ng vice-presidential and security protection group.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So our understanding is, in the office of the vice-president, an admission of Gina Acosta, that disbursement was given to some other person. The same admission was made by the DepEd SDO. Fajardo, that Fajarda, that disbursement of the funds was given to somebody else. Madam Witness?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: Yes po, tama po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And what observation? As a COA, ICFAO, State Auditor, what significance or observation can you make from these admissions by both Gina Acosta and Fajarda?
Cylene May L. Del Campo: This is a violation po of the Joint Circular, specifically yung item 6.1.1 na hindi dapat ito i-transfer from one accountable officer to another.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: No
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: further questions, Sir Lula.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you, counsel. It's 2.28. I promise the Senate President we will finish by 2.30 so that we can convene session at 3 p.m.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, respondent, attorney Christine, can you do your cross tomorrow instead of today?
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: I can, Your Honor. Your Honor, before I turn over to our head, Your Honor, may I make just this manifestation for the record just to clear?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, Counsel.
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: For avoidance, Your Honor, although we did mark the tabulations and summaries, Your Honor, for avoidance of doubt and for the record, the authenticity of the ARs are deemed established when the parties agreed and agreed with the dispensing of identification, Your Honor.
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: Your Honor, please.
Presiding officer: So
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: noted.
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: Thank you, Your Honor. Your
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: Honor,
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: please, just a counter-manifestation to her statement. You
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: may do so, counsel, before we
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: adjourn.
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: There was
Atty. Kristine R. Ferrer: no such admission, Your Honor, and there was no dispensing of identification of the ARs. Precisely, that is what the witness did today, Your Honor. Thank you.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: It is without prejudice to counsel-respondent crossing the witness using their copies of the AR, which reminds the Presiding Officer to also remind
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Your
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Honor, we'll do that. Thank you very much.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: What is the pleasure of Senator-Judge Zubiri?
Sen. Juan Miguel “Migz” F. Zubiri: Thank you very much, Mr. President. Mr. President, I could see that having the sessions for the impeachment court in the morning, we have to put a halt because of the sessions in the afternoon. May I make a suggestion that in the last week when we did our sessions, we only took about two to three hours the most. tackling our legislative calendar. May I make a suggestion that we move our legislative sessions in the morning at 10 and then have the impeachment trial at 3 in the afternoon so that we are not hampered by our legislative calendar. When discussions such as these are important, when you present evidence and the cross will be done by the
Sen. Juan Miguel “Migz” F. Zubiri: the counsels for the respondent, hindi po mapuputol yung kanilang discussion, Mr. President. Hanggang sawa tayo, pwede tayo dito from 3 to 10 ng gabi. That way, lahat ng tao po ay makakapanood din ng mga sagot nila and at the same time, we can do our work and maybe hasten the proceedings of the impeachment trial. Mr. President, that's my simple suggestion and I would like to make it into a proper motion, Mr. President. Of course, giving leeway to the Senate, to the impeachment presiding officer which days he would want to do it, Your Honors, my dear colleagues. The
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: point of the Senator-Judge, the beauty is well taken. I think we should adjust as the need arises, our session and or the impeachment trial subject to a A day's notice, I guess, to the parties before we shift. Hindi naman pwedeng the following day agad kung saka-sakaling gagawin natin. But if ever we will do it, subject to notice to the parties. Yes, Senator-Judge Villa. Kaya
Sen. Pia S. Cayetano: ito ano? Mr. Presiding Judge and Senate President, I recall we discussed this in caucus. So can we just go back into caucus? Because there were reasons we decided on this. There were reasons we decided on this. So may I humbly suggest that we, you know, take a moment and just discuss this in caucus. Plus, the minority floor leader is not here right now. So may I just humbly request that we have this discussion. Thank you.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: We won't do it yet anytime soon anyway, Senator-Judge Pia. Not anytime soon. Certainly not this week.
Sen. Juan Miguel “Migz” F. Zubiri: Mr. Presiding Officer, maybe we can make a decision by tomorrow. We can wait for the minority floor leader to attend today and we can discuss it. on caucus, and maybe by tomorrow, the presiding officer can make a decision.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, what is the pleasure of Senator-Judge Camille Villar?
Sen. Camille Villar: Yes, because I just, I remember not too long ago, our majority floor leader even brought up the idea of starting 30 minutes after, from 10 o'clock to 10.30. And then it was suggested by our other colleague that we discuss it in caucus together. So, Let's afford the same time for such decisions, right? I mean, you can't do it right away.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: We're not in a hurry to decide on this matter.
Sen. Juan Miguel “Migz” F. Zubiri: Mr. Presiding Officer, I'm just laying the predicate. It's best that we discuss this in open court now and hindi po mabulaga sila na by Monday, iba na yung schedule. Tama po yung sinabi mo. We'll give them enough time to make the adjustments. But I'd like to put that notice because last week we only had two hours of session.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: At least for
Sen. Juan Miguel “Migz” F. Zubiri: the parties, for the parties and senator
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: -judges to keep that in mind that there is such a possibility should we decide to do that after COCUS.
Sen. Juan Miguel “Migz” F. Zubiri: And I think this is more important, Mr. President. The impeachment trial, we do it in haste. We do it, proceed with, of course, with... How do you say, swiftly? So that, you know, they say, justice delayed is justice denied. So, this way, people have more time to listen to the arguments of both sides. Kasi, like last week, we only had two hours, Mr. President, Mr. Presiding Officer, per session. Umuwi tayo ng 5 o'clock in the afternoon, 5.30. Sayang din naman ito pa oras para sa impeachment court. I just put that on the table for everyone to digest and maybe we can make a decision by tomorrow. Thank you, gentlemen.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Again, the points of the good gentleman are well taken but we shall decide at the appropriate time after caucus. There being no other matters to be taken up, trial is adjourned until tomorrow at 10 a.m. Your Honor. Yes, the Honorable
Rep. Joel R. Chua: Chua. Thank you, Your Honor. Your Honor, naunawahan po namin na ngayon po ang submission ng mga pangalan po ng mga testigo para po sa susunod na linggo dahil ngayon po ay Martes. Subalit meron pa po kami tatlong mga testigo na nakasalang base po sa subpoena na in-issue po ng impeachment court. Sila po ay si Ms. Marivic Pareja, Gina Acosta, at si Edward Farda. Dahil po dito, kung inyo pong mamarapatin, Your Honor, ay bigyan po kami ng pagkakataon na bukas na magsumiti na lamang ng aming mga testigo. Depende po sa magiging resulta ng hearing.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Tama po kayo, kaya hindi yan hiniling ng presiding officer dahil may tatlo po tayong testigong nakapila na na-issue na ng subpoena para mag-attend ng pagdinig bukas. At kung hindi natin silang matatapos bukas, mag-i-issue tayo ng panibagong sabi na dun sa hindi matatalakay bukas. At kung sino mang karagdagan testigo na ayos nyo idagdag para sa susunod na linggo.
Rep. Joel R. Chua: Maraming salamat po, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you very much. There will be no other business to attend to and to take up and discuss. Trial is hereby adjourned until tomorrow, August 12 at 10 am.